<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" standalone="yes"?>
<!--DOCTYPE article PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1//EN' 'dummy.dtd'-->
<article class="techreport">
  <title>The RDBMS Backend Connector</title>
  <subtitle>Installation Guide</subtitle>

  <articleinfo>
    <author>
      <affiliation><shortaffil>Ontopia</shortaffil></affiliation>
    </author>
    <pubdate>$Date: 2008/07/21 08:18:34 $</pubdate>
    <releaseinfo>5.0 ($Revision: 1.92 $)</releaseinfo>

    <abstract>
      <para>This document is a guide to installing and configuring the
      Ontopia Topic Maps Engine RDBMS Backend Connector. It assumes
      that the reader is familiar with relational databases and has
      some knowledge of how to configure them.</para>
    </abstract>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The RDBMS Backend Connector adds relational database
    persistence support to the Ontopia Topic Maps Engine. The
    persistence is transparent and users of the topic map interfaces
    don't have to take any additional steps in order to persist topic
    maps. Applications that uses the RDBMS Backend Connector must
    properly demarcate transactions and follow the general rules in a
    transactional system. This includes managing the life-cycle of
    topic map stores and transactions.</para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>Before you can install and start using the RDBMS Backend
    Connector you must have an RDBMS server installed, and you must
    have created a database inside it. (The database can have any name
    since Ontopia finds the database name from the JDBC URL.) You also
    need a JDBC 2.0 driver, and to have set everything up so that you
    can connect to the database through the JDBC driver. If you want
    to use batch writing or connection pooling you will also have to
    install the JDBC 2.0 optional package. Once this is done, you are
    ready to start.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Requirements</title>
      
      <para>A JDBC 2.0 driver for your database must be available on
      your CLASSPATH. Your database vendor should be able to provide
      you with an appropriate JDBC driver.</para>

      <para>If you want to use connection pooling you need the JDBC
      2.0 Optional Package API (the javax.sql packages) on your
      CLASSPATH. This API can be downloaded from <ulink
      url="http://java.sun.com/products/jdbc/download.html">Sun
      Microsystems</ulink>.</para>
      
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Unicode support</title>

      <para>Ontopia fully supports Unicode, but
      for the RDBMS Connector to support Unicode the database must
      support storing Unicode text. Most databases do not enable this
      by default, and require special options to be set when creating
      the database. This section documents these options for various
      databases. Note that you need only do this if you actually need
      to store Unicode characters in your database.</para>

      <para>If you don't do this, the tests in the test suite that
      verify Unicode support will fail. This will give failure reports
      like the ones shown below.
      </para>

<screen format="linespecific">
There were 4 failures:
1) testFile(net.ontopia.topicmaps.xml.test.AbstractCanonicalTests$CanonicalTestCase) "test file unicode.xtm canonicalized wrongly"
2) testFile(net.ontopia.topicmaps.xml.test.AbstractCanonicalTests$CanonicalTestCase) "test file unicode.iso canonicalized wrongly"
3) testExport(net.ontopia.topicmaps.xml.test.AbstractCanonicalExporterTests$CanonicalTestCase) "test file unicode.xtm canonicalized wrongly"
4) testExport(net.ontopia.topicmaps.xml.test.AbstractCanonicalExporterTests$CanonicalTestCase) "test file unicode.iso canonicalized wrongly"
</screen>

      <section>
        <title>PostgreSQL</title>

        <para>To create a database which stores text in UTF-8, give
        the <parameter>-E UNICODE</parameter> option to
        <command>createdb</command>, as in
        <command>createdb -E UNICODE topicmaps</command>. More
       information can be found on the
        <ulink
        url="http://www.postgresql.org/docs">PostgreSQL</ulink>
        website.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
      <title>MySQL</title>

      <para>To create a database which stores text in UTF-8 and uses case-insensitive collation, use the following DDL command:</para>

<literallayout>
CREATE DATABASE topicmaps DEFAULT CHARACTER SET utf8 DEFAULT COLLATE utf8_bin;
</literallayout>
      </section>

      <section>
      <title>Oracle</title>

      <para>To modify a database to store text in UTF-8,
       execute the following commands. More information is available
       on <ulink
       url="http://download-west.oracle.com/docs/cd/B10501_01/server.920/a96529/ch10.htm#1009580">Oracle
       technet</ulink>.</para>

<literallayout>
STARTUP MOUNT;
ALTER SYSTEM ENABLE RESTRICTED SESSION;
ALTER SYSTEM SET JOB_QUEUE_PROCESSES=0;
ALTER DATABASE OPEN;
ALTER DATABASE CHARACTER SET UTF8;
SHUTDOWN NORMAL;
</literallayout>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the database schema</title>

      <para>The next step is to create the topic map database schema
      in the database. This is done by executing the SQL scripts
      provided in one of the <filename>*.create.sql</filename> files,
      found in the <filename>$ONTOPIA_HOME/rdbms/setup</filename>
      directory. If there is no script for the database you are using,
      use the <filename>generic.create.sql</filename> script.</para>

      <para>There are also scripts for dropping the database
      schema in the same directory.</para>

      <para>These scripts create the tables with primary keys and
      indexes in the database. They also initialize the
      <symbol>TM_ADMIN_SEQUENCE</symbol> table by inserting a single
      row. The <symbol>TM_ADMIN_SEQUENCE</symbol> table contains the
      sequence counters used to generate object identities.</para>

      <para>In later versions we will provide a command-line tool
      which initializes the database for you automatically. In the
      meantime, if you run into problems when initializing the
      database, please send an email to <ulink
      url="mailto:support@ontopia.net">support@ontopia.net</ulink>.
      </para>

      <para>The next step is to create a properties file that contains
      the information necessary to connect to the database.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Microsoft SQL Server 2005</title>

        <para>Only SQL Server 2005 or newer versions are
supported. Older versions may work, but there will be contention in
the database if used in a concurrent environment.</para>

        <para>In order to enable the snapshot isolation and row
versioning features (both needed by Ontopia) the following two
statements need to be executed in the database. Replace the
<symbol>topicmaps</symbol> name with the name of your database. Note
that this will not work with the <symbol>master</symbol> database as
the <symbol>read_committed_snapshot</symbol> is not supported in that
database. Use a custom database instead.</para>

<literallayout>
alter database topicmaps set allow_snapshot_isolation on;
alter database topicmaps set read_committed_snapshot on;
</literallayout>

        <para>More information about the database features can be found <ulink
      url="http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/library/tcbchxcb(VS.80).aspx">here</ulink>.</para>

      </section>
      
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Setting up the properties file</title>

      <para>Before we can connect to the database we need to tell the
      backend how to connect to the database. This is done by writing
      a Java properties file that provides the necessary
      information. Below are listed the properties that need to be
      defined. You can put the properties file anywhere you like, but
      it is recommended to place it together with other configuration
      files. For Ontopia to find this file you have to point to it
      from the <filename>tm-sources.xml</filename> file. (See the
      Navigator Congiguration guide for details.)</para>

      <para>The default properties file for use in applications can be
      designated by setting the
      <symbol>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.PropertyFile</symbol>
      system property to the property filename. Note that the default
      can always be overridden through the APIs.</para>

      <para>A collection of sample database properties files can be
      found in the <symbol>$ONTOPIA_HOME/rdbms/config</symbol>
      directory.</para>
              
    <section>
      <title>Database connection</title>

<variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.Database</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: token, Required: yes</para>
           <para>This property specifies which database it is running
           against. The RDBMS Backend Connector uses this information
           to adjust the SQL it generates, and also to do
           optimizations.</para>

            <para>Possible values are: <symbol>oracle8</symbol>,
            <symbol>oracle9i</symbol>, <symbol>oracle10g</symbol>,
            <symbol>postgresql</symbol>, <symbol>mysql</symbol>, <symbol>h2</symbol>
            <symbol>sqlserver</symbol> and
            <symbol>generic</symbol>. If you don't find your database
            in this list try using the <symbol>generic</symbol>
            setting.</para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.ConnectionString</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: string, Required: yes</para>
           <para>This is the JDBC connection string, which must be
           specified.  The value will depend on which database you
           are using and how you have configured it.</para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.DriverClass</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: string (class name), Required: yes</para>
           <para>This is the fully qualified class name of the JDBC
           driver class to use. It must be set. Note that this must
           be a JDBC 2.0 driver.</para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.UserName</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: string, Required: yes</para>
           <para>This is the user name of the database user.</para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.Password</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: string, Required: yes</para>
           <para>This is the password of the database user.</para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.BatchUpdates</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Type: boolean, Default: false</para>
            <para>If set to <symbol>true</symbol> all database modifications
             will be performed through JDBC batch updates.</para>

            <para>This option boosts performance with large
            transactions and in environments where network lag is an
            issue, since the number of network requests needed is
            significantly lower and the database may provide
            optimizations for performing lots of similar database
            modifications in batches.</para>

            <para>Note that some JDBC drivers do not support batch
            updates. Please verify that your JDBC driver actually
            supports batch updates before enabling it.</para>
         </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>
      
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Clustering</title>

      <para>If multiple instances of the RDBMS Backend Connector are
      to access the same topic map(s) the clustering feature
      <emphasis>must</emphasis> be enabled to prevent
      inconsistencies. As each instance holds an internal data cache
      any modifications to the data needs to be replicated across all
      nodes in the cluster. This must be done to prevent any of the
      nodes from holding stale data.
      </para>

      <warning>
        <para>Note that if your application uses the Web Editor
        framework then another clustering configuration needs to the
        set up. See the <citetitle><ulink
        url="../webed/devguide.html">Web Editor Framework Developer's
        Guide</ulink></citetitle> for more information.</para>
      </warning>

      <warning>
        <para>Note that nodes in the cluster must use distinct license
        keys.</para>
      </warning>
      
      <variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.Cluster.id</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>Type: string, Default: none</para>

            <para>This property specifies the id of the cluster that
            the instance should be a member of. All instances that
            access the same topic map should be members of the same
            cluster. Specifying this property will make the instance
            connect to to the cluster on startup.</para>
            
            <para>The cluster identifier must start with
            <symbol>jgroups:</symbol>,
            e.g. <symbol>jgroups:cluster:my-topicmaps</symbol>. JGroups
            is currently the only clustering implementation for cache
            invalidation.</para>
          </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.Cluster.properties</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>Type: string, Default: none</para>

            <para>This property lets one pass in the name of a file
            containing configuration properties used by the clustering
            implementation. If the property is not specified the
            default properties will be used. The file will be first
            attempted loaded from the file system, then from the
            classpath.</para>
          </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>

     <para>Note that there is a critical bug in pre-1.6 JVMs related
     to IPv6 network support that prevents them from being used with
     JGroups out of the box. To make JGroups use IPv4 make sure that
     you pass the following system property to the JVM on
     startup:</para>

<literallayout><![CDATA[
-Djava.net.preferIPv4Stack=true
]]></literallayout>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Caching</title>

      <para>The RDBMS Backend Connector retrieves all its data from
      the backing relational database. The communication with the
      database is relatively fast, but can introduce a big performance
      hit when the network traffic is high. In order to offer high
      performance Ontopia provides a number of client-caches that
      makes it possible to avoid repeated reads from the database.
      </para>

      <variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.Cache.shared</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>Type: boolean, Default: true</para>

            <para>Because the RDBMS Backend Connector supports
            concurrent transactions the database communication needs
            to be effective and non-redundant. Ontopia provides a
            cache implementation that transactions can share, so that
            redundant database access is avoided. This cache is
            enabled by default when using the Navigator and Web Editor
            Frameworks. Note that when using the Topic Maps Engine API
            one must access the topic map store through one of the
            topic map source implementations in the RDBMS Backend to
            make use of the shared cache. Warning: If one does not use
            the shared cache in a multi-user environment the
            performance hit can be very high.</para>

            <para>The only situation where you should consider
            disabling this cache is when you have one long-running
            transaction. In this case it is best to disable the shared
            cache because it adds an overhead and can, if the
            transaction is big, also cause the transaction to run out
            of memory. Without a shared cache there is no limit on the
            size of transactions.</para>

            <warning>
            <para>Do not disable the shared cache when there
            are concurrent transactions updating the
            same topic map as this would mean that the transactions
            might not see each other's committed changes.</para>
            </warning>

          </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.Cache.identitymap.lru</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>Type: integer (# items in cache), Default: 300</para>

            <para>Each transaction maintains a mapping between the
            object ids of topic map objects and the topic map objects
            themselves. This data structure holds soft references to
            the topic map objects and the objects can therefore be
            garbage collected when there are no other hard references
            to them. This is a mechanism that lets the Java Virtual
            Machine get rid of objects when it needs to reclaim memory
            in order to not run out of memory. This datastructure is
            also extremely useful for the transaction itself because
            it uses it to avoid having to create object instances too
            often.</para>

            <para>This property tells Ontopia that it should hold hard
            references to the most recently used objects and for how
            many objects it should do so. Note that the property
            specifies the number of hard references per transaction,
            so when adjusting this number take into account how many
            concurrent transactions you might have and how much memory
            is available.</para>
          </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.Cache.shared.identitymap.lru</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>Type: integer (# items in cache), Default: 5000</para>

            <para>This property is similiar to the previous one, but
            this one is used to define the size of the lru of the
            shared identity map. The shared identity map is shared
            amongst all read-only transactions. In general this one
            should be bigger than the previous one as there are
            usually a lot more read-only transactions in the system
            than read-write ones.</para>
          </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.Cache.subjectidentity.srcloc.lru</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>Type: integer (# items in cache), Default: 2000</para>

           <para>Each transaction maintains cache that is a mapping
           between source locators and the topic map objects that
           have those identities. This cache is there so that
           repeated lookups can be fast. The cache uses soft
           references and this property lets you specify how many
           hard references there should be to the most recently used
           entries.</para>

            <para></para>
          </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.Cache.subjectidentity.subind.lru</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>Type: integer (# items in cache), Default: 1000</para>

           <para>Each transaction maintains cache that is a mapping
           between subject identities (subject identifiers) and the
           topics that have those identities. This cache is there so
           that repeated lookups can be fast. The cache uses soft
           references and this property lets you specify how many
           hard references there should be to the most recently used
           entries.</para>
          </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.Cache.subjectidentity.subloc.lru</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>Type: integer (# items in cache), Default: 100</para>

           <para>Each transaction maintains cache that is a mapping
           between subject locators and the topics that have those
           identities. This cache is there so that repeated lookups
           can be fast. The cache uses soft references and this
           property lets you specify how many hard references there
           should be to the most recently used entries.</para>
          </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.Cache.rolesbytype.lru</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>Type: integer (# items in cache), Default: 1000</para>

           <para>This setting is used to control the minimum size of a
           cache used by the <symbol>TopicIF.getRolesByType(TopicIF
           roleType)</symbol>. This cache is also used by the tolog
           query engine to improve association traversal
           performance.</para>
          </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.Cache.rolesbytype2.lru</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>Type: integer (# items in cache), Default: 1000</para>

           <para>This setting is used to control the minimum size of a
           cache used by the <symbol>TopicIF.getRolesByType(TopicIF
           roleType, TopicIF associationType)</symbol>. This cache is
           also used by the tolog query engine to improve association
           traversal performance.</para>
          </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

    </section>
              
    <section>
      <title>JDBC connection pooling</title>

      <para>The RDBMS Backend Connector uses JDBC connections to
      access the relational database. Being able to reuse connections
      across interactions with the database is important because
      creating connections is expensive. The RDBMS Backend Connector
      supports different JDBC connection pool implementations. Use the
      following properties to enable and configure connection
      pooling:</para>

<variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.ConnectionPool</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: boolean, 'dbcp' or 'jndi',
                Default: dbcp</para> 

                  <para>If set to <symbol>true</symbol>, or any of the
                  named collection pool implementations, connection
                  pooling will be used. The default connection pool
                  implementation is 'dbcp'. It is recommended that one
                  use connection pooling if one needs to open more
                  than a single topic map transaction.</para>
          </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <!--varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.ConnectionPool.InitialSize</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: integer (# connections), Default: 1</para>

                        <para>Specifies the number of connections that are
                        to be created when the connection pool is
                        instantiated.</para> </listitem>
       </varlistentry-->
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.ConnectionPool.MinimumSize</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: integer (# connections), Default: 20</para>

                 <para>The minimum number of connections in the
                 pool. The number of connections in the pool will
                 never shrink below this size.</para> </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.ConnectionPool.MaximumSize</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: integer (# connections), Default: Integer.MAX_VALUE</para>

                 <para>The maximum number of connections in the
                 pool. The number of connections will never grow
                 larger than this number, unless the soft maximum is
                 enabled.</para>
                 </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.ConnectionPool.SoftMaximum</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: boolean, Default: true</para>

                 <para>If the maximum pool size is reached but there
                 are outstanding requests for connections emergency
                 connections will be created if this property is
                 true. This will temporarily increase the size of the
                 pool, but the pool will shrink back to an acceptable
                 size when the activity is lower. If this setting is
                 false, requests will block until a connection is
                 available.</para> </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.ConnectionPool.PoolStatements</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: boolean, Default: true</para>

                 <para>The dbcp connection pool makes it possible to
                 pool and reuse prepared statements created by the
                 application. The RDBMS Backend uses prepared
                 statements and enabling this feature should
                 generally have a positive effect on performance. If
                 the connection pool is dbcp then this feature is
                 enabled by default. You should only set this
                 property to false if you have a good reason to do
                 so.</para>
          </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <!--varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.ConnectionPool.Timeout</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: integer (# seconds), Default: 1200</para>
           <para>Connections will be removed after living for a duration
           longer than this value.</para>
         </listitem>              
       </varlistentry-->
       <!--varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.ConnectionPool.UserTimeout</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: integer (# seconds), Default: 0 (never)</para>

                 <para>A user will lose a connection and it will be
                 returned to the pool after the duration greater than
                 or equal to this value. Be careful when using this
                 setting. If the value is 0 there will be no
                 timeout.</para> </listitem>
       </varlistentry-->
       <!--varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.ConnectionPool.SkimmerFrequency</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: integer (# seconds), Default: 420</para>

                  <para>Specifies how often each object's connection
                  timeout and user timeout values will be examined for
                  collection.</para> </listitem>
       </varlistentry-->
       <!--varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.ConnectionPool.ShrinkBy</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: integer (# objects), Default: 5</para>

                 <para>Specifies the maximum number of connections
                 that should be allowed to be removed from the pool
                 every time it is shrunk.</para> </listitem>
       </varlistentry-->
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.ConnectionPool.JNDIDataSource</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: string (the JNDI name), Default: none</para>

                <para>Specifies the JNDI name of the JDBC data
                source. Note that this property is only useful when
                you are accessing the JDBC connections via
                JNDI. This usually only happens inside an J2EE
                application server. The property must be specified
                if the 'jndi' connection pool implementation has
                been specified. If you do not use JNDI to configure
                and set up your JDBC connections then do not set
                this property.</para>
          </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
      
    </section>
              
    <section>
      <title>Topic map store pooling</title>

      <para>Ontopia supports pooling of topic map stores in the same
      way as you can pool JDBC connections with the provided
      connection pool implementations. The topic map store pooling is
      currently only available via the topic map reference
      implementation in the RDBMS Backend Connector. When using the
      RDBMS Backend Connector with the Navigator and Web Editor
      frameworks the topic map store pooling is always enabled. Note
      that when using the Topic Maps Engine API one must access the
      topic map stores through one of the topic map source
      implementations in the RDBMS Backend to make use store
      pooling. These topic map source implementations always use store
      pooling.</para>

      <para>The main reason for using topic map store pooling is that
      it greatly improves performance in transactional
      environements. This is possible because topic map objects, topic
      map data, cached information and other state information can be
      reused across transaction boundaries.</para>

      <para>You can override the store pool defaults by setting the
      following properties:</para>

      <variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.StorePool.MinimumSize</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: integer (# stores), Default: 0</para>

                 <para>The minimum number of stores in the pool. The
                 number of stores in the pool will never shrink below
                 this size.</para> 
          </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.StorePool.MaximumSize</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: integer (# stores), Default: 8</para>

                 <para>The maximum number of stores in the pool. The
                 number of stores will never grow larger than this
                 number, unless the soft maximum is enabled.</para>
                 </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.StorePool.SoftMaximum</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: boolean, Default: false</para>

                 <para>If the maximum pool size is reached but there
                 are outstanding requests for stores emergency stores
                 will be created if this property is true. This will
                 temporarily increase the size of the pool, but the
                 pool will shrink back to an acceptable size when the
                 activity is lower. If this setting is false,
                 requests will block until a connection is
                 available.</para> </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      
    </section>
              
    <section>
      <title>Tolog queries</title>

      <para>The RDBMS Backend Connector has its own tolog
      implementation which it will use if it finds that it is possible
      to translate the tolog query into SQL. In most of the cases the
      entire tolog query can be translated fully into a SQL query, but
      for some more complex tolog queries only parts or none of it can
      be translated. Sometimes it makes sense for a topic map
      application to not use the RDBMS tolog implementation. These
      applications can change the default tolog implementation by
      setting the following property:</para>

      <variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.query.core.QueryProcessorIF</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: 'in-memory' or 'rdbms', Default:
                'in-memory'</para> 

                  <para>Specifies which tolog implementation the RDBMS
                  Backend Connector should use by default.</para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

    </section>
              
    <section>
      <title>Fulltext queries</title>

      <para>The tolog query language with its value-like predicate
      uses an underlying Fulltext integration. At the moment there are
      two options. The first is 'generic', which means that the search
      terms is turned into a SQL expression using the LIKE operator
      with wild cards on both sides. The second is 'oracle_text' which
      translates the search into an Oracle Text search expression. It
      is possible to specify exactly which Fulltext integration that
      should be used:</para>

      <variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.infoset.fulltext.impl.rdbms.RDBMSSearcher.type</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: 'generic' or 'oracle_text', Default:
                'generic'</para> 

                  <para>Specifies which fulltext implementation the RDBMS
                  Backend Connector should use by default.</para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      
      <para>Note that this property will also have an effect with
       direct use of the
       <classname>net.ontopia.infoset.fulltext.impl.rdbms.RDBMSSearcher</classname>
       class.</para>
      
    </section>
              
    <!--section>
      <title>Database platform settings</title>

      <variablelist>

       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.Platforms</term>
         <listitem>
       <para>Type: list of tokens, Default: inferred from Database property</para>
           <para>A comma-separated list (note: no whitespace) of
           platform fallbacks. "postgresql,generic" means that if
           platform declarations for e.g. queries are set to
           "postgresql" then it will be used, otherwise the "generic"
           declaration will be used and so on. Note that "generic"
           must always be included in the list.</para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.HighLowKeyGenerator.SelectSuffix</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>Type: string, Default: "for update" (no suffix)</para>
            <para>The RDBMS Backend Connector maintains a counter for
            the object identities that it creates. In order for the
            incrementing to behave properly and in a safe manner the
            reading and modifications of that value must be atomic and
            block all others from doing the same at the same
            time.</para> 

           <para>The property should be set to e.g. "for update" if
           the database supports locking rows via select
           statements. The suffix is appended to the select statement
           that the key generator uses for retrieving the current
           sequence counter value. Each database might have it's own syntax for this, but the default is </para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.KeyBlockSize</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>Type: integer, Default: 200</para>
           <para>This is the number of object identities the key
           generator should preallocate each time. The number to use
           depends on how many objects are to be created in the
           transactions. Note that if the key generator runs out of
           allocated identities it allocates another block in the
           database. The reason to use a somewhat higher number is to
           avoid unnecessary database traffic.</para>

            <para>Note that a new database connection is created for
            every new key block requested. This number can be kept low
            if connection pooling is used.</para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.persistence.query.sql.InMaxElements</term>
         <listitem>
          <para>Type: integer, Default: Integer.MAX_VALUE
          (unlimited)</para> <para>Some databases support only a
          certain number of values in the SQL <symbol>IN</symbol>
          clause. If the database has a known limit then this property
          should be set to the maximum number of allowed values to be
          used in this clause. This setting is normally used only by
          the RDBMS tolog query implementation.</para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>
      
    </section-->
              
    <!--section>
      <title>O/R Mapping files</title>

      <para>The RDBMS Backend Connector requires two additional
      configuration files. The first one is a mapping file that
      describes the mapping between the database schema and the topic
      map object model. The second contains all queries that are used
      by the topic map implementation. The OKS is able to locate the
      default mapping files automatically.</para>

      <para>In the rare situations where you'd want to override the
      default mapping files you can use the following
      properties:</para>

      <variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.MappingFile</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: string (file name), Default:
           ${propfile.dir}/mapping.xml</para>
           <para>The filename of the object-relational mapping
           file. This file contains the mapping between the database
           schema an the topic map object model.</para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.QueriesFile</term>
         <listitem>
                <para>Type: string (file name), Default:
           ${propfile.dir}/queries.xml</para>
           <para>The filename of the query declarations file. This
           file contains all the queries used by the topic map
           implementation.</para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>
      
    </section-->
              
    <section>
      <title>Sample file</title>

      <example>
       <title>Sample properties file (Oracle)</title>
       
       <literallayout format="linespecific" class="normal"><![CDATA[
net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.Database=oracle10g
net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.ConnectionString=jdbc:oracle:thin:@127.0.0.1:1521:TOPICMAPS
net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.DriverClass=oracle.jdbc.driver.OracleDriver
net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.UserName=scott
net.ontopia.topicmaps.impl.rdbms.Password=tiger
]]></literallayout>
      </example>
 
<warning>
<para>
Please note that the backslash character (<literal>\</literal>) is
used as an escape character in Java property files. If you need to
write a backslash (for example in DOS paths), make sure you write them
as <literal>\\</literal>. Lines ending in a single backslash will
cause the following property to be ignored.
</para>
</warning>
    </section>
</section>

    <section>
      <title>Native RDBMS full-text</title>

      <para>Instead of using the Lucene integration with the RDBMS
      Backend Connector one can take advantage of the native full-text
      support that the database may have. This support can range from
      simple LIKE operator queries to advanced full-text indexing
      support. Starting with version 2.0 of the OKS Enterprise Edition
      one can make use of these native features.</para>

      <para>In the
      <symbol>net.ontopia.infoset.fulltext.impl.rdbms</symbol> package
      there is a class called <symbol>RDBMSSearcher</symbol> that
      implements the <symbol>SearcherIF</symbol> interface. Pass your
      RDBMS <symbol>TopicMapIF</symbol> instance to the single
      constructor of this class and you have a searcher instance that
      let you search for topic name, variant name, and occurrences using
      the native pattern language.</para>

      <para>The actual queries that are issued and the syntax that are
      supported is usually database specific, but the default
      behaviour is to use the LIKE operator. This means that you can
      use the '%' symbol to specify wildcards in your queries. Most
      relational databases support the LIKE operator, and therefore
      the default should be ok for most databases. Note that the
      actual query will make use of the <symbol>lower</symbol> function
      to make it a case-insensitive query.</para>

      <para>In addition to the generic RDBMS full-text support the OKS
      comes has support for several database-specific full-text
      implementations. They are all described below.</para>

      <para>Note that enabling native RDBMS full-text through the <symbol>net.ontopia.infoset.fulltext.impl.rdbms.RDBMSSearcher.type</symbol> database property will also enable it for the
<symbol>value-like</symbol> tolog predicate.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Oracle Text</title>

      <para>Recent versions of Oracle comes with full-text
support included. The component is called Oracle Text. In older versions Oracle
Text was an optional component and had to be purchased and installed
separately.</para>

      <para>To enable use of  Oracle Text in the OKS you will have to set the
      <symbol>net.ontopia.infoset.fulltext.impl.rdbms.RDBMSSearcher.type</symbol>
      database property to
      <symbol>oracle_text</symbol>. You will also have to make sure that the
      columns <symbol>TM_TOPIC_NAME.content</symbol>,
      <symbol>TM_VARIANT_NAME.content</symbol>, and
      <symbol>TM_OCCURRENCE.content</symbol> are setup to be indexed
      by Oracle Text.</para>

      <para>Here are some sample statements to set this up for
      Oracle. Note that they require the Oracle Context Option, which
      for Oracle 8.x needs to be installed separately, but for Oracle
      9i and later it should be installed by default.</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[
create index TEXT_TOPIC_NAME on TM_TOPIC_NAME(content) 
  indextype is ctxsys.context 
  parameters ('sync(on commit) datastore ctxsys.default_datastore filter ctxsys.null_filter section group ctxsys.auto_section_group');
create index TEXT_OCCURRENCE on TM_OCCURRENCE(content) 
  indextype is ctxsys.context 
  parameters ('sync(on commit) datastore ctxsys.default_datastore filter ctxsys.null_filter section group ctxsys.auto_section_group');
create index TEXT_VARIANT_NAME on TM_VARIANT_NAME(content) 
  indextype is ctxsys.context 
  parameters ('sync(on commit) datastore ctxsys.default_datastore filter ctxsys.null_filter section group ctxsys.auto_section_group');
]]></programlisting>

    <para>These indexes will be kept up to date on every commit. If
    you don't need to have them synced that often, consider changing
    the sync parameter.</para>

<!--
      <para>Be aware that Oracle Text does not keep the indexes up to
      date automatically. A possible solution to this is to make sure
      that the ctxsrv process is running and altering the indexes so
      that they are rebuilt automatically. Note that this is not
      neccessarily what you want.</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[
alter index TEXT_TOPIC_NAME rebuild online parameters('sync memory 45M'); 
alter index TEXT_OCCURRENCE rebuild online parameters('sync memory 45M');
alter index TEXT_VARIANT_NAME rebuild online parameters('sync memory 45M'); 
]]></programlisting>
-->

      <para>An error message will be issued by the Oracle RDBMS if one
      attempts to use the Oracle Text query when the columns have not been
      full-text indexed, so if this happens you will have to run the
      create index statements above or similar ones.</para>

      <para>Please consult your database documentation for more
      information on Oracle Text.</para>

      <!--para>You can customize the queries by modifying the
      'RDBMSSearcher.searchLike' query in your queries.xml file. Note
      that the queries.xml file that is currently shipped with the OKS
      is stored inside the <symbol>oks-enterprise.jar</symbol>
      file. You will need to unzip the file to modify the
      <symbol>queries.xml</symbol> file.</para-->

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>PostgreSQL full-text</title>

      <para>The full-text support in PostgreSQL is implemented through
a module called <ulink
url="http://www.sai.msu.su/~megera/postgres/gist/tsearch/V2/">tsearch2</ulink>. This
module will usually have to be installed manually before it can be
used. This is typically done by logging in as the PostgreSQL
administrator user and running the
<filename>${PSQL_LIB}/contrib/tsearch2.sql</filename> script in the
database, e.g. using the <symbol>psql</symbol> command line
utility. If you later which to uninstall tsearch2 that can be done
with the <filename>${PSQL_LIB}/contrib/untsearch2.sql</filename>
script.</para>

    <para>The next step is to grant access to the tsearch2 tables to
the database user that is used by the OKS. Replace
<symbol>myuser</symbol> with the name of your database user below.</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[
grant all on pg_ts_cfg to myuser;
grant all on pg_ts_cfgmap to myuser;
grant all on pg_ts_dict to myuser;
grant all on pg_ts_parser to myuser;
]]></programlisting>
  
      <para>tsearch2 will then have to be told which of its configurations that are to be used. The OKS uses a configuration called <symbol>default</symbol>. The configurations are mapped to the server encoding. Issue the following statement to set the locale for the default configration.</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[
update pg_ts_cfg set locale='en_US.UTF-8' where ts_name='default';
]]></programlisting>

      <para>If you don't know what the server encoding is then the following query will tell you:</para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
select setting from pg_settings where name='lc_ctype';
]]></programlisting>

      <para>The last step is to add a tsearch2 column and an index to
each of the three tables that are to be searched. To keep the index
up-to-date a set of triggers will also have to be added.</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[
/* add columns */
alter table TM_TOPIC_NAME add column tsearch2 tsvector;
alter table TM_VARIANT_NAME add column tsearch2 tsvector;
alter table TM_OCCURRENCE add column tsearch2 tsvector;
/* create indexes */
create index tsearch2_index_tbn on TM_TOPIC_NAME using gist(tsearch2);
create index tsearch2_index_tvn on TM_VARIANT_NAME using gist(tsearch2);
create index tsearch2_index_to on TM_OCCURRENCE using gist(tsearch2);
/* populate indexed columns */
update TM_TOPIC_NAME set tsearch2=to_tsvector('default', coalesce(content,''));
update TM_VARIANT_NAME set tsearch2=to_tsvector('default', coalesce(content, ''));
update TM_OCCURRENCE set tsearch2=to_tsvector('default', coalesce(content, ''));
/* add triggers */
create trigger tsearch2_update_tbn before update or insert on TM_TOPIC_NAME for each row execute procedure tsearch2(tsearch2, content);
create trigger tsearch2_update_tvn before update or insert on TM_VARIANT_NAME for each row execute procedure tsearch2(tsearch2, content);
create trigger tsearch2_update_to before update or insert on TM_OCCURRENCE for each row execute procedure tsearch2(tsearch2, content);
]]></programlisting>

      <para>To enable use of tsearch2 in the OKS you will have to
set the
<symbol>net.ontopia.infoset.fulltext.impl.rdbms.RDBMSSearcher.type</symbol>
database property to <symbol>postgresql</symbol> or <symbol>tsearch2</symbol>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Microsoft SQL Server full-text</title>

      <para>The full-text support in SQL Server is not enabled by default, so it will have to be enabled:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[
EXEC sp_fulltext_database 'enable';
]]></programlisting>

      <para>Then a full-text catalog has to be created and one
full-text index added to each of the three tables that are be
indexed. The database server will keep the full-text indexes
automatically up to date as changes occur.</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[
create fulltext catalog okscatalog as default;
create fulltext index on TM_TOPIC_NAME(content) key index TM_TOPIC_NAME_pkey;
create fulltext index on TM_VARIANT_NAME(content) key index TM_VARIANT_NAME_pkey;
create fulltext index on TM_OCCURRENCE(content) key index TM_OCCURRENCE_pkey;
alter fulltext catalog okscatalog reorganize;
]]></programlisting>

      <para>Note that the <symbol>TM_TOPIC_NAME_pkey</symbol>,
<symbol>TM_VARIANT_NAME_pkey</symbol> and
<symbol>TM_OCCURRENCE_pkey</symbol> indexes referenced above are
primary key indexe names, but they may not actually have those names in
your database. You will have to look up the actual names of those
three indexes of the given three names don't work.</para>

      <para>To enable use of Microsoft SQL Server full-text in the OKS you will have to
set the
<symbol>net.ontopia.infoset.fulltext.impl.rdbms.RDBMSSearcher.type</symbol>
database property to <symbol>sqlserver</symbol>.</para>
                
    </section>
                
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Setting the CLASSPATH</title>

      <para>In order for the Java Virtual Machine to be able to load
      the RDBMS Backend Connector classes you need to add the
      ontopia.jar file to your <envar>CLASSPATH</envar> environment
      variable. See the <citetitle>Ontopia
      Installation and getting started</citetitle> document for more
      information.</para>

                     <para>Note that you also need to put your selected JDBC-driver
                     classes on the <envar>CLASSPATH</envar>.</para>

                     <para>If you are using batch writing or connection pooling, then
                     you must make sure that the JDBC 2.0 optional package is
                     available on the <envar>CLASSPATH</envar>.</para>
                     
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Running the test suite</title>
      
      <para>Now that you have an empty database we are ready to verify
      that the system actually works. We do this by running the test
      suite on the database. If you don't want to run the test suite,
      feel free to skip this section.</para>

      <para>Before you can run the RDBMS Backend Connector test suite
      make sure that you have the Ontopia test
      environment correctly set up. This includes having the ontopia.jar and ontopia-test.jar-files on the CLASSPATH. See
      the <citetitle>Ontopia, Installation and getting
      started</citetitle> document for more information.</para>
                     
      <para>You can now run the test suite by following the procedure
      below:</para>

      <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Windows</term>
                            <listitem>
        <para>Go to the <filename>${basedir}</filename>
        directory. Set the environment variable
        <envar>ONTOPIA_HOME</envar> to the <symbol>${basedir}</symbol>,
        using the command
        <command>set ONTOPIA_HOME=${basedir}</command>. Then run the
        <command>tests\runtests-rdbms.bat</command> script passing the
        property file as an argument.</para>
                            </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Unix</term>
                            <listitem>
        <para>Go to the <filename>${basedir}</filename>
        directory. Then run the
        <command>tests/runtests-rdbms.sh</command> script passing the
        property file as an argument.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      
      <para>The result should be similiar to what is shown below. If
      it is not, please send an email to <ulink
      url="mailto:support@ontopia.net">support@ontopia.net</ulink>
      with the output of the test run as well as details about your
      platform and the database you are using.</para>

      <screen format="linespecific">
Ontopia RDBMS Backend Connector [version]
License: [license info]
Success: All required classes found.
Running tests
.........................................
.........................................
.........................................
.........................................
.........................................
.........................................
.........................................
..............................
Time: [xxx.yyy]

OK ([zzz] tests)

Asserts: [nnn]
</screen>
  </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>What's next?</title>

    <para>Congratulations. Now that you've gotten this far it is time
    to start developing software using the RDBMS Backend
    Connector. See the <citetitle><ulink
    url="devguide.html">Ontopia RDBMS Backend Connector,
    Developer's Guide</ulink></citetitle> for information about how to
    develop applications using the backend connector.</para>
    
  </section>

</article>
