<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" standalone="yes"?>
<!--

  Hi! This is a text file. If you're making a simple change, please
  don't use an editor which reindents the entire file. Thank you. 

  TODO

    - update oks-now.png

    - rewrite all the content

    - add vizigator

-->

<!--?xml-stylesheet href="../docbook.css" type="text/css"?-->
<!--DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" ""-->
<article class="whitepaper"> 
<title>The Ontopia Knowledge Suite</title>
<subtitle>An Introduction</subtitle> 

<articleinfo> 
  <author> 
    <affiliation> 
   <orgname>Ontopia A/S</orgname> 
    </affiliation> 
  </author> 
  <pubdate>$Date: 2006/05/07 13:05:53 $</pubdate> 
  <releaseinfo>3.1 ($Revision: 1.41 $)</releaseinfo> 
  <abstract> 
    <para> This whitepaper gives a quick introduction to version 3.1 of the
   Ontopia Knowledge Suite (OKS), describing the architecture, functionality, and
   composition of the suite. There is also some discussion of the possible usage
   areas of the suite. </para> 
    <para> A basic understanding of the main concepts of topic maps is
   assumed; for explanations of these, please see 
   <ulink url="http://www.ontopia.net/topicmaps/articles.html">the topic
    map introductions on our web site</ulink>. </para> 
  </abstract> 
</articleinfo> 

<!-- ===== OVERVIEW ============================================================-->
<section> 
<title>An overview of the OKS</title> 

<para>
The Ontopia Knowledge Suite is a well-designed suite of products
that together enable the development of diverse types of topic map-enabled
applications. The suite is designed to be integrated into any application to
provide it with topic map capabilities. It is stable, performant, and highly
advanced; it handles all the difficult aspects of developing with topic maps
for you.
</para> 

<para> 
In version 2.1 the suite consists of five main products, with
several smaller add-on components. These can be purchased in three different
configurations, which are described below. The main products are:
</para> 

<variablelist> 
  <varlistentry> 
    <term>The Ontopia Topic Map Engine</term> 
    <listitem> 
      <para>This is the heart of the suite: a Java SDK which has all
      the functionality needed for writing software that works with
      topic maps. The engine loads, stores and keeps track of the
      topic maps, and provides interfaces through which applications
      can access and manage the topic maps. The other products in the
      OKS are built on the engine and use its functionality.</para>

      <para>Three add-on components to the Engine provide additional
      power for advanced applications. These are the query engine,
      which supports a topic map query language, the schema tools,
      which support a topic map schema language, and the full-text
      integration, which adds support for full-text search of topic
      map data.</para>
    </listitem> 
  </varlistentry> 
  <varlistentry> 
    <term>The Ontopia Navigator Framework</term> 
    <listitem> 
    <para>The Ontopia Navigator Framework greatly simplifies the
    development of topic map driven web applications. It is based on
    Java Servlets and Java Server Pages (JSP), and provides a set of
    tag libraries and Java components that make developing scalable
    topic map web applications with advanced functionality fast and
    easy. Using it can be compared with using a kind of XSLT specially
    designed for topic maps.</para>
    </listitem> 
  </varlistentry> 
  <varlistentry> 
    <term>The Ontopia Web Editor Framework</term> 
    <listitem> 
    <para>The Ontopia Web Editor Framework is based on the same
    technology than the Ontopia Navigator Framework.  It is designed
    to enable customers to build user-friendly web editing
    applications based on customer-specific requirements. Instead of
    providing a generic interface where the user has to be familiar
    with the topic map concept the framework makes it possible to edit
    topic maps without knowing that you are working with topic
    maps.</para>
    </listitem> 
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry> 
    <term>The Ontopia Vizigator</term> 
    <listitem> 
    <para>The Ontopia Vizigator provides graphical visualization of
    topic maps making it possible to see connections and structures in
    an intuitive display of the topic map. Application developers can
    use a graphical tool to configure the display by filtering
    associations and topics and fine-tuning their visual appearance.
    The visualizations can then be deployed on the web using Java
    applets.</para>
    </listitem> 
  </varlistentry> 
  <varlistentry> 
    <term>The Ontopia RDBMS Backend Connector</term> 
    <listitem> 
    <para>This add-on to the engine enables it to store topic maps in
    relational databases, and to access and modify topic maps stored
    in such databases. Most RDBMS servers are supported.</para>
    </listitem> 
  </varlistentry> 
</variablelist> 

<para> 
In addition to these main products, the OKS contains some smaller
components which add important functionality to the suite. These are:
</para>

  <variablelist> 
    <varlistentry> 
   <term>The query engine</term> 
   <listitem> 
    <para>Using the query engine you can easily specify complex criteria
        for retrieving information from the topic map. This greatly simplifies
        application development, since much can be accomplished with very little code,
        and significantly lowers the learning curve for developers.</para> 
    <para>Since queries specify retrieval actions at a very high level
        they also provide great scope for optimization, allowing the query engine to
        perform retrieval very efficiently.</para> 
   </listitem> 
    </varlistentry> 
    <varlistentry> 
   <term>The Ontopia Full-text Search Integration</term> 
   <listitem> 
    <para>The full-text integration allows users to look up topics by
        name (and text appearing in occurrences) easily and quickly. This allows users
        to jump to a specific point in a topic map immediately, without knowing the
        topic map structure at all, which makes it enormously much easier to find
        information.</para> 
   </listitem> 
    </varlistentry> 
    <varlistentry> 
   <term>The Ontopia Schema Tools</term> 
   <listitem> 
    <para>Certain tasks can only be performed by humans, but humans make
        mistakes. If your topic maps are written by human authors, in whole or in part,
        you will want some way of ensuring that the authors use the correct topic map
        structure. Using the Ontopia Schema Language you can easily and concisely
        define the correct topic map structure and use the schema tools to enforce that
        structure.</para> 
   </listitem> 
    </varlistentry> 
    <varlistentry> 
   <term>The Omnigator</term> 
   <listitem> 
    <para>The Omnigator is a demonstration tool built using the Navigator
        Framework. It is a topic map browser that can be used to browse any topic map.
        Ontopia has made the Omnigator freely available in order to promote topic map
        awareness, but it is also distributed as part of the OKS, as many customers
        have found it useful for looking at their own topic maps. (One customer called
        it a <quote>topic map debugger</quote>.)</para> 
   </listitem> 
    </varlistentry> 
  </variablelist> 
  <para> Below is a diagram that shows the structure of the OKS, and the
    relationship between the different parts. </para> 
  <figure> 
    <title>The OKS at version 2.1</title>
    <graphic fileref="oks-now.png" format="PNG"/> 
  </figure> 
  <para> Future versions will add more products and components. </para> 
  <section> 
    <title>Editions of the Suite</title> 
    <para> The OKS comes in three different editions: </para> 
    <variablelist> 
   <varlistentry> 
    <term>Personal edition</term> 
    <listitem> 
        <para>This edition contains the Engine, which means that it is
       mostly useful for integration and visualization projects, and for adding topic
       map functionality to existing products.</para> 
    </listitem> 
   </varlistentry> 
   <varlistentry> 
    <term>Professional edition</term> 
    <listitem> 
        <para>This edition contains the Engine with the three add-on
       components, the Navigator Framework, as well as the Web Editor Framework. It is
       useful for prototype web projects, smaller web projects, and for adding topic
       map-capabilities to existing products which need a web interface.</para> 
    </listitem> 
   </varlistentry> 
   <varlistentry> 
    <term>Enterprise edition</term> 
    <listitem> 
        <para>This edition adds the RDBMS backend to the professional
       edition, and is thus the edition of choice for deployment of full-scale
       projects.</para> 
    </listitem> 
   </varlistentry> 
    </variablelist> 
    <para> The table below shows more precisely which components are included
   in what editions of the OKS. The prices of the different editions as well as an
   online purchasing system can be found 
   <ulink url="http://www.ontopia.net/solutions/products.html">on our web
    site</ulink>. </para> 

    <table> 
      <title>OKS editions</title> 
      
      <tgroup cols="4"> 
        <thead> 
          <row> 
            <entry>Component</entry> 
            <entry>Personal</entry> 
            <entry>Professional</entry> 
            <entry>Enterprise</entry> 
          </row> 
        </thead> 
        <tbody> 
          <row> 
            <entry>Engine</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
          </row> 
          <row> 
            <entry>Omnigator</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
          </row> 
          <row> 
            <entry>Query engine</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
          </row> 
          <row> 
            <entry>Schema tools</entry> 
            <entry>&#160;</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
          </row>
          <row> 
            <entry>Full-text search</entry> 
            <entry>&#160;</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
          </row> 
          <row> 
            <entry>Navigator</entry> 
            <entry>&#160;</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
          </row> 
          <row> 
            <entry>Web Editor Framework</entry> 
            <entry>&#160;</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
          </row> 
          <row> 
            <entry>Vizigator</entry> 
            <entry>&#160;</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
          </row>    
          <row> 
            <entry>RDBMS Backend</entry> 
            <entry>&#160;</entry> 
            <entry>&#160;</entry> 
            <entry>Yes</entry> 
          </row> 
        </tbody> 
      </tgroup> 
    </table> 
  </section> 
  <section> 
    <title>Application areas for the Suite</title> 
    <para> The Ontopia Knowledge Suite is not an end-user product, but a set
   of tools useful for building such products. In general, the Suite can be used
   to advantage in nearly any application that manages information. The problem
   solved by the Ontopia Knowledge Suite is the perennial problem of information
   management: the problem of navigating the information ocean to find the
   knowledge you seek. </para> 
    <para> We all know how difficult it can be to find the information you
   are looking for. The reasons for this are many and deep-rooted, and not the
   least of them is that creating appropriate information structures is in itself
   difficult. Topic maps, the product of decades of work and experience in
   information management, provide a model for the organization of information
   that can make creating appropriate structures much easier. If your information
   repository is organized with a topic map, structuring it becomes much easier,
   and so locating the document or piece of information you want also becomes much
   easier. </para> 
    <para> An important aspect of topic maps is that they do not require you
   to replace your information repository with one based on topic maps. Instead,
   you can maintain a topic map <emphasis>separately</emphasis> from your
   repository and have the topic map refer into the repository. The topic map can
   then be navigated to locate the information you need from the repository.
   </para> 
    <para> With the Ontopia Knowledge Suite you have what you need to create
   and manage topic maps for your repositories, as well as to build the interfaces
   used to navigate the resulting topic maps. Using the Ontopia Knowledge Suite
   all the difficult problems of topic map management, persistence, concurrency,
   transactions, and scalability are taken care of for you. </para> 
    <para> Some of the most important and interesting areas where the
   Knowledge Suite can simplify development and improve the result are: </para> 
    <itemizedlist> 
   <listitem> 
    <formalpara> 
        <title>Web portals</title> 
        <para>Portals, being essentially large information repositories,
       are perfect use cases for the OKS. Using topic maps for the portal contents you
       will find yourself guided by the topic map model into creating a well-organized
       portal. Using the OKS developing the actual portal is greatly simplified,
       thanks to the Ontopia Topic Map Navigator SDK.</para> 
    </formalpara> 
   </listitem> 
   <listitem> 
    <formalpara> 
        <title>Knowledge-base intranets</title> 
        <para>Using topic maps you can capture and manage the knowledge
       that constitutes the corporate memory in a kind of semantic network that
       represents people, products, roles, procedures, and other artefacts of your
       organization; the relationships between these entities; and the links to the
       documentation that describe them in detail. With the OKS you can enrich your
       intranet with topic maps and turn it into a real collaborative knowledge
       base.</para> 
    </formalpara> 
   </listitem> 
   <listitem> 
    <formalpara> 
        <title>Content management systems</title> 
        <para>Any content management system can benefit from a better and
       more flexible way of organizing information, which is what topic maps provide.
       Using the Ontopia Topic Map Engine you can integrate topic mapping capabilities
       into your content management system. The integration could take the form of
       making the entire system topic map-based, or it could create a virtual topic
       map of the system. And with the Ontopia Topic Map Navigator the web interface
       is there almost out of the box. For more information about how content
       management issues can be applied using the topic map paradigm please see 
       <ulink
       url="http://www.ontopia.net/topicmaps/materials/itms.html">here</ulink>.</para>
        
    </formalpara> 
   </listitem> 
   <listitem> 
    <formalpara> 
        <title>Enterprise Application Integration (EAI)</title> 
        <para>The topic map data model is designed to allow automated
       merging of information from diverse sources. Using the Ontopia Topic Map
       Engine's support for merging, you can easily integrate information from many
       different sources into a coherent whole. This can be used to integrate the
       products in a product suite, as well as to finally allow the many separated
       applications of an enterprise to appear as a single whole. A web interface to
       this unified information can be developed using the Navigator framework.</para>
        
    </formalpara> 
   </listitem> 
    </itemizedlist> 
    <para> The list of possible application areas for this technology is
   endless, and as topic map technology is still new and fresh exciting new uses
   for it will undoubtedly continue to be found. </para> 
    <para> Below is a figure that shows how the Ontopia Knowledge Suite might
   be used to build a web site based on topic maps, storing the topic map data in
   a relational database. </para> 
    <figure> 
   <title>Web application built on the OKS</title>
   <graphic fileref="current-arch.gif" format="GIF89a"/> 
    </figure> 
    <para> In this example the web application is deployed in a Java 2
   Platform, Enterprise Edition (J2EE) web server, together with the Ontopia
   Engine and Navigator. The topic map is stored in a relational database server,
   managed by the engine, and the web application is built using the navigator
   framework. </para> 
  </section> 
</section> 

<!-- ===== NAVIGATOR ==================================================-->
<section> 
<title>The Ontopia Topic Map Navigator</title> 

<para> The most natural way to access the information in a topic map today
  is through the web, and the Ontopia Topic Map Navigator greatly simplifies
  development of topic map web applications. The Navigator is a general
  development framework based on the engine that lets you create your own web
  interfaces to your topic maps. </para> 
<para> The framework consists of a set of Java utility APIs designed for
  web development, and a set of JSP tag libraries. The tag libraries allow much
  of the logic in each web page to be written using XSLT-like tags, thus
  dramatically simplifying the development process. The tag libraries are very
  high-level and allow developers to do scope filtering and other advanced
  operations simply by tweaking the attributes of tags. </para> 
<para> Another important benefit to the tag libraries is that since they
  operate at a high level of abstraction, they allow for many advanced
  optimizations, like caching of the most frequently retrieved topic names,
  object pooling, and so on. Thread-safety, session management, and so on is also
  handled automatically by the framework. Applications using the tag libraries
  get these benefits with no extra effort. The tag library is also integrated
  with the tolog query language, allowing you to use tolog queries to build your
  web applications. </para> 
<para> The framework is fully internationalized and can correctly render
  topic maps written in any script. We have successfully viewed both Chinese and
  Japanese topic maps in our navigator applications. Applications built using the
  navigator inherit these features with no extra effort required. </para> 
<para> The navigator framework is based on the Java 2 Platform, Enterprise
  Edition (J2EE), and applications developed with it can be deployed into any
  J2EE container. The 
  <ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/">Tomcat</ulink> web server
  was used during development, but using an automated test suite it is easy to
  verify that the navigator works in other containers as well. We have verified
  that the Navigator works in the 
  <ulink url="http://www.caucho.com/products/resin/">Resin</ulink>
  application server as well. </para> 
<section> 
  <title>The Omnigator</title> 
  <para> As a demonstration of the power of the navigator framework we have
 developed the Omnigator, which is short for 'the omnivorous topic map
 navigator'. This is a topic map web application that can be used to navigate
 any topic map. You can access an online demo of the Omnigator at 
 <ulink url="http://www.ontopia.net/omnigator/models/index.jsp">the
  Ontopia web site</ulink>. </para> 
  <para> Although written for demonstration purposes, the Generic Navigator
 is a useful tool in its own right, since it turns any topic map into a web site
 with no need for programming at all. This makes it very useful as a tool for
 quickly creating topic map prototype applications that can be used to test out
 the applicability of topic maps to specific problems (and also to convince
 management that topic maps are the correct approach). All that is needed is to
 generate your topic maps as XML documents, load them into the Navigator, and
 you have a simple but convincing topic map demo.</para> 
  <para> Below is shown a screenshot from the Omnigator, showing the
 automatically generated page for a topic in Steve Pepper's Italian Opera topic
 map. The topic shown is Puccini, a well-known composer. </para> 
  <figure> 
 <title>The Omnigator</title>
 <graphic fileref="navigator-shot.gif" format="GIF89a"/> 
  </figure> 
  <para> The Omnigator is an advanced topic map application, supporting all
 aspects of both the XTM 1.0 and ISO 13250 standards. Some of the more advanced
 concepts supported are listed below. </para> 
  <itemizedlist> 
 <listitem> 
  <formalpara> 
      <title>Reification</title> 
      <para>Refification allows topics to represent identifiable
     resources within a computer, such as a web resource or a construct in a topic
     map. This can be used to make statements about associations, topic names,
     resources, and even occurrences (that is, the relationship between a topic and
     a resource). The navigator recognizes reification and uses it to optimize its
     presentation of the topic map. (See 
     <citetitle>The Omnigator User's Guide</citetitle> for examples of
     reification.)</para> 
  </formalpara> 
 </listitem> 
 <listitem> 
  <formalpara> 
      <title>Scope</title> 
      <para>Scope can be attached to occurrences, names and associations
     to say what contexts they are valid. This can be used to enable multiple views
     on single topic map, for example by language or in other ways. The Omnigator
     includes a User Context Filter plug-in (described below) that automatically
     builds user preference forms based on the use of scope in the topic map.</para>
      
  </formalpara> 
 </listitem> 
  </itemizedlist> 
  <para> These concepts are also supported by the underlying framework,
 which makes it easy to develop topic map web applications using these
 constructs. </para> 
</section> 
<section> 
  <title>Using the Navigator Framework</title> 
  <para> The screenshot from the Opera topic map above shows the same view
 that is presented by the Omnigator for <emphasis>all</emphasis> topics. This is
 so because the Omnigator is designed to display any topic map, and so does not
 know the difference between a composer, a country, or an engine part. Using the
 Navigator Framework you can develop web applications that are specific to your
 topic maps, and this allows you to give the applications a user interface
 designed for your topic map. Below is shown the page for Puccini in the
 Operamap web application, which is written with the Navigator Framework, and
 designed for the Opera topic map. </para> 
  <figure> 
 <title>The Operamap application</title>
 <graphic fileref="operamap-shot.gif" format="GIF89a"/> 
  </figure> 
  <para> The application is simple, and yet it shows that a topic
 map-driven web site can look just like any other web site, except that it is
 easier to find your way around. Using the navigator framework, writing this
 page is very simple. Most of the page is produced by a template, which is used
 to ensure that the site has a common look and feel. The rest of the page is
 produced by the <filename>composer.jsp</filename> file, which produces the
 pages for composers. It fills the area with the main content by pulling
 information from the topic map and writing it out as HTML. </para> 
  <para> Below is shown the JSP code used to produce the list of operas.
 Like XSLT the code is a mix of HTML elements (which are written out as output)
 and logic elements, which are executed to produce the output. </para> 
  <example> 
 <title>List of operas</title> 
 <literallayout><![CDATA[ <logic:set name="composed">
  <tm:associated from="composer" type="composed-by"/> </logic:set>
  <p><b>Operas:</b><br /> <logic:foreach name="composed"> <li><a
  href="opera.jsp?id<output:objectid/>"><output:name/></a> <logic:set
  name="date"> <tm:filter
  instanceOf="premiere-date"><tm:occurrences/></tm:filter> </logic:set>
  <logic:if name="date"> <logic:then> <output:content of="date"/> </logic:then>
  </logic:if> </li> </logic:foreach> </p> ]]></literallayout> 
  </example> 
  <para> The code first finds all topics associated with the composer via
 the <symbol>composed-by</symbol> association, which gives us the list of operas
 (automatically sorted by name). We then loop over the operas (using
 <symbol>logic:foreach</symbol>), and write an HTML list item for each opera,
 with a link to that opera. We also find the <symbol>premiere-date</symbol>
 occurrence of the opera, and, if there is one, we write out its contents. This
 is the white text you see after the name of each opera. </para> 
  <para> In this way, creating a web application for a topic map becomes a
 matter of no more than writing some HTML and topic map tags. No Java
 development is necessary, although if desired it is possible to integrate Java
 code into the framework in various ways. The full power of the topic map
 engine, the tolog query language, and the full-text search is available to
 application developers. </para> 
</section> 
<section> 
  <title>User context filter</title> 
  <para> The navigator framework as well as the Omnigator support a user
 context filter. The user can set to control what parts of the topic map the web
 application is to show them. This filter uses the scopes defined in the topic
 map, and lets users decide which names they prefer to see, and what occurrences
 and associations they do not wish to see. </para> 
  <para> This feature can be used to let users decide which language they
 want to see a topic map in, if the topic map has names in several languages for
 each topic. They can also decide whether they want to see the full names of
 topics, for example, or just the abbreviated forms. </para> 
  <para> In very information-rich topic maps, with many occurrences and
 associations for each topic, the filter may be used to remove occurrences and
 associations that are less interesting to the user, in order to keep the amount
 of information presented to a manageable level. </para> 
  <para> Users can control the settings of the user context filter by
 following the 'Filter' link shown in the screenshot above. </para> 
</section> 
<section> 
  <title>Rendering with Model-View-Skin</title> 
  <para> The Navigator Framework uses a Model-View-Skin approach to
 rendering topic maps, cleanly separating graphical layout from information
 extraction. This simplifies application development, and allows application
 developers and graphic designers to collaborate more easily. </para> 
  <itemizedlist> 
 <listitem> 
  <formalpara> 
      <title>View</title> 
      <para>A view is essentially a web page template, written as a JSP
     page, with a set of named slots where content can be filled in. This makes it
     easy for graphic designers to create a single template for all pages in an
     application, thus simplifying the development, and at the same time separating
     application development from graphic design.</para> 
  </formalpara> 
 </listitem> 
 <listitem> 
  <formalpara> 
      <title>Model</title> 
      <para>The model is a JSP page that generates blocks of content and
     attaches them to the named slots defined by the view. The model pages are
     generally written by application developers, and do all the hard work of
     extracting information from the topic map and other sources, and turning it
     into web page content.</para> 
  </formalpara> 
 </listitem> 
 <listitem> 
  <formalpara> 
      <title>Skin</title> 
      <para>The last piece of the puzzle, the skin, is simply a 
     <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/Style/CSS/">CSS stylesheet</ulink>
     that is applied to the generated page to produce the page style. This will
     generally define aspects such as the colors, background, fonts and text size.
     </para> 
  </formalpara> 
 </listitem> 
  </itemizedlist> 
  <para> The end-user using the web application sees the combination of a
 model, a view and a skin, and each user can freely select whichever combination
 is found the most appealing. For example, the Omnigator has both a frame-view
 and a no-frames-view. Each user can freely select which view to use. Similarly,
 the Omnigator has a detail model, displaying as much information as possible,
 and a simple model, showing only essential information. </para> 
  <para> A set of skins are provided with the Omnigator, ranging from the
 tasteful to the less so. New skins can be added simply by copying them into a
 specific directory. Users can freely combine views, models, and skins as
 desired. </para> 
</section> 
<section> 
  <title>Extending the Navigator with plug-ins</title> 
  <para> The Navigator has a concept of <firstterm>plug-ins</firstterm>,
 which allows extensions to topic map web applications to be developed
 separately from the applications and easily plugged in. The plug-ins can be
 deployed by simply dropping them into a directory, and the navigator will
 automatically detect their presence and include them in the interface. </para> 
  <para> Essentially, a plug-in is a web page that is linked to from every
 page of a topic map web application. When users follow this link, the web page
 is informed about the current topic map and topic, and can thus present
 relevant information. The topic map statistics plug-in, for example, will use
 these parameters to display statistics about the current topic map. </para> 
  <para> This mechanism allows plug-ins to be developed separately from
 specific topic map web applications and yet to be easily integrated into them.
 The result is greatly simplified development, installation, and administration.
 </para> 
</section> 
<section> 
  <title>The Navigator plug-ins</title> 
  <para> The Omnigator comes with a set of plug-ins which can be helpful
 when creating topic maps and developing web applications. These plug-ins are:
 </para> 
  <itemizedlist> 
 <listitem> 
  <formalpara> 
      <title>Statistics reporter</title> 
      <para>The statistics reporter is a simple plug-in that provides
     statistics about a topic map, such as the number of topics, the number of
     topics of each type, the association structure of the topic map, and so
     on.</para> 
  </formalpara> 
 </listitem> 
 <listitem> 
  <formalpara> 
      <title>Merge plug-in</title> 
      <para>The merge plug-in allows you to merge any topic map in the
     navigator's topic map registry with the current topic map, and enters the
     merged topic map into the navigator as a new topic map. You can then browse the
     resulting topic map in the navigator. This allows you to easily and quickly
     test the effects of automatically merging topic maps.</para> 
  </formalpara> 
 </listitem> 
 <listitem> 
  <formalpara> 
      <title>Export</title> 
      <para>The export plug-in allows topic maps to be exported in either
     ISO 13250 or XTM 1.0 format, and to be viewed or downloaded. Two topic maps can
     be merged using the merge plug-in and then exported in merged form using the
     export plug-in. Topic maps can also be loaded in one format (XTM, ISO, or LTM)
     and exported in another.</para> 
  </formalpara> 
 </listitem> 
 <listitem> 
  <formalpara> 
      <title>Full-text search</title> 
      <para>This plug-in comes with the full-text integration product and
     makes it very easy to do full-text searches on the topic map. Results are
     displayed in an intuitive manner, with links both into the topic maps and to
     any external resources in which matches were found.</para> 
  </formalpara> 
 </listitem> 
  </itemizedlist> 
  <para> More plug-ins are likely to be developed in the near future, since
 the simplicity of the plug-in concept makes it very easy to develop new
 plug-ins. A number of trivial examples in addition to those mentioned here are
 distributed with the Omnigator. </para> 
</section> 
</section> 
  

<section> 
  <title>The Web Editor Framework</title> 
  <para>Often topic maps can be generated automatically from existing data
    sources, but sometimes they may not be sufficient. Sometimes, the knowledge
    required by an application simply doesn't already exist in the system. In
    situations like this manual topic map creation and maintenance is used to add
    value to the autogenerated topic map.The Ontopia Web Editor Framework is a
    component of the Professional Edition and Enterprise Edition.</para> 
  <para>The Web Editor Framework provides the functionality to build
    user-friendly editing environments. Instead of subjecting users to all the
    complexities of topic map, custom applications can be developed that doesn't
    require users to know that they are working with topic maps.</para> 
  <figure> 
    <title>Editing application built using the Web Editor
   Framework</title><graphic fileref="edit-screen.png"/> 
  </figure> 
  <section> 
    <title>Customized vs generic editing interfaces</title>

    <para>The Web Editor Framework enables you to build a customized
    editor for your specific ontology. However, not all users wish to
    do this, and for such users Ontopia is developing a generic
    editor. This editor (OmniEditor) will let users define their own
    ontologies, which will then be used to drive the editing
    interface. OmniEditor should be adequate for any users who do not
    require highly customized interfaces, and which do not require
    complex updating logic. If you are interested in beta-testing the
    OmniEditor, please send an email to <email>sales@ontopia.net</email>.
    </para>
  </section> 
  <section> 
    <title>Applying the Web Editor Framework</title> 
    <para>The Web Editor Framework is an extension of the Navigator
   Framework. It is assumed that you have read through the previous chapter where
   the Navigator Framework was discussed.</para> 
    <para>The Web Editor Framework includes tag libraries for the tasks of
   adding, modifying and deleting topic map constructs. Applications built using
   the Navigator Framework can be easily reused and just extended with the adding
   functionality. The interface to the user is form-based. </para> 
    <para>The web developer writes JSP pages which produce HTML pages
   containing HTML forms. The forms and fields included in the HTML are connected
   to actions on the server which are triggered when the form is submitted. The
   input fields, e.g. text input fields, buttons and lists are connected with
   topic map objects, e.g. topics, associations, occurrences etc. </para> 
    <para>Furthermore the following features are supported</para> 
    <variablelist> 
   <varlistentry> 
    <term></term> 
    <listitem> 
        <para>Declarative specification of application control flow</para> 
    </listitem> 
   </varlistentry> 
   <varlistentry> 
    <term></term> 
    <listitem> 
        <para>Concurrent authoring and transaction handling</para> 
    </listitem> 
   </varlistentry> 
   <varlistentry> 
    <term></term> 
    <listitem> 
        <para>File- und RDBMS-based storage</para> 
    </listitem> 
   </varlistentry> 
   <varlistentry> 
    <term></term> 
    <listitem> 
        <para>The libraries provide you with the most common actions but it
       is possible to create your own custom actions</para> 
    </listitem> 
   </varlistentry> 
    </variablelist> 
  </section> 
  </section>

  <section> 
  <title>The Ontopia Topic Map Engine</title> 
  <para> The Ontopia Topic Map Engine is what topic map applications and
    products use to work with topic maps. This SDK lets applications load topic
    maps from XML documents, store topic maps in databases, modify and access topic
    maps, and generally do all an application may need to do with a topic map. The
    engine has a core topic map API, which all applications use to access topic map
    data, regardless of where those data are stored. Thus, whether the topic map is
    in-memory, in a database, or a virtual view is all the same to the application.
    </para> 
  <para> The Ontopia Topic Map Engine is the product of three years of topic
    map software development and sports a number of impressive features, as well as
    some powerful add-on components. The features are described immediately below,
    while the components are described in separate sections below. </para> 
  <variablelist> 
    <varlistentry> 
   <term>A well-designed API</term> 
   <listitem> 
    <para>The core API of the engine has been carefully designed to be
        consistent, intuitive, and scalable. A number of well-considered policies
        describing the rules topic map data must abide by have been designed and
        documented. The result is an API that is quickly learned, and that protects the
        integrity of the underlying topic map data. The core API consists only of data
        objects, with all action objects separated out. This separation means that the
        core API is essentially only a thin layer over the underlying data.</para> 
    <para>The core APIs provide an object model that fully supports both
        the ISO 13250 standard and the XTM 1.0 specification. All aspects of the models
        of both standards are supported, as are extensions for other addressing
        syntaxes than URIs.</para> 
   </listitem> 
    </varlistentry> 
    <varlistentry> 
   <term>Extensive utilities</term> 
   <listitem> 
    <para>A rich set of utilities built on the core API is provided.
        These utilities provide functions like topic map-wide deletion of topics,
        association walking, filtering characteristics by scope, name selection, and
        topic map merging. The utilities are general and will work for any
        implementation of the core API.</para> 
   </listitem> 
    </varlistentry> 
    <varlistentry> 
   <term>The index API</term> 
   <listitem> 
    <para>The engine also has an index API which can be used for quickly
        and efficiently looking up information about the topic map, such as all
        instances of a given type, all topics that have been used as topic types, all
        topics used as scopes for occurrences, and so on. This API enables applications
        to quickly and efficiently locate the information they need, and also provides
        a mechanism for inferring information about the design of the topic map.</para>
    
   </listitem> 
    </varlistentry> 
    <varlistentry> 
   <term>XML import and export</term> 
   <listitem> 
    <para>The engine has APIs for importing and exporting topic maps to
        and from XML documents. There is full support for the XTM 1.0 format and all
        its features, as well as for an XML version of the ISO 13250 format. Topic maps
        can easily be imported from one format and exported into the other. There is
        also support for validating XTM topic maps against a DTD and verifying that
        there are no dead references.</para> 
    <para>There is also support for importing topic maps from the compact
        and easy-to-author 
        <ulink url="http://www.ontopia.net/download/ltm.html">LTM
       format</ulink> developed by Ontopia. This can be used to author and demo simple
        topic maps very quickly.</para> 
   </listitem> 
    </varlistentry> 
    <varlistentry> 
   <term>Cross-platform support</term> 
   <listitem> 
    <para>The Engine is written in pure Java (though not certified as
        such), and has been tested with the Java 2 Software Development Kit (SDK) 1.3
        on Windows 98, Windows 2000, RedHat Linux 7.0, SuSE Linux 7.1, Debian Linux
        2.2, and Solaris SunOS 5.7. No known platform dependencies are in the code, and
        so it should run on any platform that has a Java 1.3 environment.</para> 
   </listitem> 
    </varlistentry> 
    <varlistentry> 
   <term>Internationalization support</term> 
   <listitem> 
    <para>The Engine correctly imports and exports topic maps to and from
        any legacy encodings supported by Java, which means that most character
        encodings are supported. Use is also made of the internationalization features
        of Java to provide internationalized sorting and similar operations.</para> 
   </listitem> 
    </varlistentry> 
    <varlistentry> 
   <term>Comprehensive test suite</term> 
   <listitem> 
    <para>To support the development and maintainance of the engine we
        have developed an extensive automated test suite for the engine. This test
        suite consists of more than 1000 test cases and verifies that all aspects of
        the engine are working correctly. All aspects of the core APIs, the utilities,
        the XML import/export, and the index API are tested. This ensures that the
        quality of the engine is high and that it remains so over time.</para> 
    <para>The test suite is shipped with the product, which enables
        customers to quickly verify that the engine works correctly in their particular
        environment. The test suite is also used to verify that the various
        implementations of the core APIs behave identically.</para> 
   </listitem> 
    </varlistentry> 
    <varlistentry> 
   <term>Enterprise-level robustness</term> 
   <listitem> 
    <para>The engine has been tested extensively to verify that it is
        thread-safe, scalable, and performant. A collection of automated testing tools
        has been developed to verify that the engine maintains these properties as new
        features continue to be added.</para> 
   </listitem> 
    </varlistentry> 
  </variablelist> 
  <section> 
    <title>The architecture of the engine</title> 
    <para> As is shown in the diagram below topic map applications access the
   topic map data through the core APIs and the topic map utilities. The utilities
   also use the core APIs, and so all interaction with the topic map data happen
   passes through the core interfaces. Import and export of topic maps serialized
   as XML, whether in XTM 1.0 or ISO 13250 format, is also done through the core
   interfaces. </para> 
    <figure> 
   <title>The engine architecture</title>
   <graphic fileref="EngineArch.png"/> 
    </figure> 
    <para> This architecture allows applications and utilities to be
   implemented independently of how topic map data are represented. The data can
   be an in-memory object structure (which is what this diagram shows), a special
   implementation that stores its data in a relational database, or even a virtual
   view onto another data source. All applications and utilities will still work
   with the topic map in the same way. </para> 
  </section> 
  <section> 
    <title>The Query Engine</title> 
    <para> The Query Engine is an implementation of the tolog query language
   for topic maps. This language can query topic maps for topics of specific
   types, which participate in certain combinations of associations, and supports
   inference rules. You can sort query results, and there is also support for
   counting query matches, and sorting by counts. </para> 
    <para> Using tolog allows complex retrieval operations to be expressed
   compactly and easily, making it easier to develop and maintain applications.
   tolog is <emphasis>not</emphasis> a standardized query language, but is
   provided while ISO completes its standardized TMQL query language. Once
   completed, Ontopia will provide full support for TMQL. </para> 
    <para> The query engine analyzes queries in order to find the most
   efficient way to perform the query, which means that using queries generally
   yields much more efficient code than implementing the query yourself on top of
   the APIs. The effort of writing a query is also of course at least an order of
   magnitude smaller. </para> 
    <para> More information on the tolog query language is available in 
   <ulink url="http://www.ontopia.net/topicmaps/materials/tolog.html">an
    early paper</ulink> presented at XML Europe 2001, as well as 
   <ulink
      url="http://www.ontopia.net/omnigator/docs/query/tutorial.html">the tolog
    language tutorial</ulink>. </para> 
  </section> 
  <section> 
    <title>The Schema Tools</title> 
    <para> The Schema Tools are an implementation of the Ontopia Schema
   Language (OSL), which is a schema language for topic maps that allows the
   expression of constraints on a topic map. For example, it can be used to say
   that composers must have only a single name, they must have a date of death and
   of birth, and they must have composed at least one opera. </para> 
    <para> Using the Schema Tools applications can easily validate whether or
   not the topic maps they work with follow the prescribed topic map structure or
   not. Schemas are also useful as compact and precise documentation of the
   structure of a topic map. </para> 
    <para> The main use for the Schema Tools is to ensure that human authors
   follow the editorial guidelines laid down in a particular topic map project,
   but they can also be used to guard against unpleasant surprises in
   automatically generated topic maps. </para> 
    <para> OSL is described in 
   <ulink
      url="http://www.ontopia.net/omnigator/docs/schema/tutorial.html">the OSL
    tutorial</ulink>. </para> 
  </section> 
  <section> 
    <title>The Full-text Search Integration</title> 
    <para> The Full-Text Integration allows topic maps to be indexed and then
   searched for topics by their names and the contents of their occurrences. This
   can be very helpful for users new to topic maps who need to find something
   quickly in a topic map. Using the full-text search they can type the name of
   what they are looking for and immediately be presented with a list of
   alternative topics. From the topics they can then easily find the information
   they are looking for. </para> 
    <para> Using full-text searching in this way gives users an entirely
   different user experience, since although they are doing an unstructured search
   the users get a result set that is anything but unstructured. Since users are
   shown their search results in terms of topic map constructs it is much easier
   to judge <emphasis>what</emphasis> they have found, and one can more easily
   search for obscure or vague concepts by searching for related topics and then
   navigating around. </para> 
    <para> The Java-based search engine 
   <ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/lucene/docs/">Lucene</ulink>
   comes bundled with the integration. Lucene is open source, powerful, robust,
   scalable, and lightning fast. A plug-in for the Omnigator providing an
   easy-to-use user interface is also part of the distribution. Other full-text
   search engines can also be plugged in. You can try this out in 
   <ulink url="http://www.ontopia.net/omnigator/">the online demo</ulink>.
   For more information about Lucene please see the 
   <ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/lucene/docs/index.html">Lucene
    homepage</ulink>.</para> 
  </section> 
  <section> 
    <title>The RDBMS backend</title> 
    <para> The RDBMS backend is an add-on to the Ontopia Topic Map Engine
   that uses the architecture described in the previous section to store topic
   maps persistently in relational databases. The applications access the topic
   map data through a different implementation of the core interfaces, which means
   that applications (as well as the engine utilities) need not care how the topic
   map data are stored. The test suite is used to verify that the two API
   implementations behave in precisely the same way. </para> 
    <para> The diagram below shows the architecture of the engine with the
   RDBMS backend. </para> 
    <figure> 
   <title>The engine architecture (with RDBMS)</title>
   <graphic fileref="RdbmsArch.png"/> 
    </figure> 
    <para> Using this backend topic map application can scale to handle
   enormous topic maps, and also get benefits such as transactions and concurrency
   management between different processes. The architecture of the engine allows
   prototypes to be developed quickly using topic maps generated by scripts and
   stored in XML files. The prototype can then be upgraded to production quality
   by switching to the RDBMS backend and upgrading the generation scripts. The
   applications themselves do not need to change, since they are independent of
   where the topic maps are stored. </para> 
    <para>The RDBMS backend has been tested with Oracle 8i, PostgreSQL 7.1,
   and hsql 1.61, and is known to work with these databases. It can also be used
   with MySQL 3.23 (with the InnoDB transaction support). Whether the backend
   works on a given server or not can easily be verified using the test
   suite.</para> 
  </section> 
  </section> 
 
</article> 
