<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- Do not delete the External ID. It is needed for validation. -->
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY ted '<productname>Ontopoly</productname>'>
  <!ENTITY ots '<productname>Ontopia</productname>'>
  <!ENTITY expand '<graphic role="Expand" fileref="images/expand.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY collapse '<graphic role="Collapse" fileref="images/collapse.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY box '<graphic role="Blank Box" fileref="images/boxed.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY up '<graphic role="Up" fileref="images/up.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY down '<graphic role="Down" fileref="images/down.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY add '<graphic role="Add new value" fileref="images/add.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY add-field '<graphic role="Add field" fileref="images/expand_all.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY add-to-fields '<graphic role="Add to fields" fileref="images/add_to_fields.png"/>'>
  <!ENTITY remove-field '<graphic role="Remove field" fileref="images/remove.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY inherited '<graphic role="Inherited field" fileref="images/blank.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY create '<graphic role="Create" fileref="images/create.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY remove-value '<graphic role="Remove field" fileref="images/remove-value.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY dnd '<graphic role="Drag and drop to reorder" fileref="images/dnd.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY goto '<graphic role="Goto topic type that assigns field" fileref="images/goto.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY goto-uri '<graphic role="Navigate to address" fileref="images/goto.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY goto-details '<graphic role="Edit field details" fileref="images/goto-details.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY search '<graphic role="Find topic" fileref="images/search.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY assign-field '<graphic role="Assign field" fileref="images/assign-field.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY help '<graphic role="Contextual help" fileref="images/help.gif"/>'>
  <!ENTITY save-icon '<graphic role="Save" fileref="images/save-icon.png"/>'>
]>
<!-- $Id: user-guide.xml,v 1.51 2009/05/22 08:20:34 geir.gronmo Exp $ -->
<!--
     markup conventions:

     * terms like "Topic Map Index Page": first occurrence <firstterm>,
       thereafter just capitalisation
     * filenames, directory names: <filename>
     * button names: <guibutton>
     * syntax: <symbol>
-->
<article>
<title>&ted;: The Topic Map Editor</title>
<subtitle>User&#8217;s Guide</subtitle>

<!--Additions for future:
    - localization support;
    - up/down arrows affect spinner - other keystrokes affect search
      box;
    - load config menu item;
    - instance editor embedding
-->

<articleinfo>
<author>
<affiliation><orgname>Ontopia</orgname>
</affiliation>
</author>
<pubdate>$Date: 2009/05/22 08:20:34 $</pubdate>
<releaseinfo>5.0 ($Revision: 1.51 $) </releaseinfo>

<abstract>
<para>This is the user guide for Ontopia&#8217;s self-configuring, ontology-driven
Topic Maps editor, &ted;. A topic map consists of both an ontology
and an instance of that ontology; with &ted;, you can edit each of these.
The ontology defines the rules for what can go into the instance, and
these rules are used by &ted; to automatically generate the interface
for creating and maintaining the instance. This document provides guidance
for creating both ontologies and instances.</para>

<para>Reading this document assumes some basic knowledge about Topic
Maps. If you are not familiar with Topic Maps, try reading one of the
simple introductions, such as <ulink
url="http://www.ontopia.net/topicmaps/materials/tao.html">The TAO of
Topic Maps</ulink>, available from the Ontopia web site. If you are
technically minded, you might also want to look at the <ulink
url="http://www.topicmaps.org/xtm/1.0/">XTM Specification</ulink> or
the new version of ISO 13250, especially the <ulink
url="http://www.isotopicmaps.org/sam/sam-model/">Data
Model</ulink>.</para>

<para> We welcome any suggestions you might have on ways of improving
this User Guide. Please send them to
<email>dev@ontopia.net</email>.</para>

<para>We hope you enjoy using &ted;!</para>

</abstract>
</articleinfo>

<section>
<title>Getting started</title>

<para>&ted; is built as a client/server application. As a client, you
use your web browser, while the server is a web server bundled with the
distribution. The server-side application is built using the
<productname>Navigator Framework</productname> and <productname>Web
Editor Framework</productname>, which are parts of the
<productname>Ontopia Knowledge Suite&#x2122;</productname>. &ted; is
accessible within &ots;, an application that provides easy access to
&ted;, <productname>Omnigator</productname>, and
<productname>Vizigator</productname>.</para>

<figure id="ots-home-pg-fig">
<title>&ots; Home Page</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_home_page.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>To install and start up &ots;, please see
<command>install.html</command>. Once you have accessed &ots;, choose
&ted; from the available options.</para>
</section>

<section id="gen-concepts">
<title>General concepts</title>

<section id="overview">
<title>Application architecture</title>

<para>&ted;&#8217;s primary purpose is to enable the manual creation and
maintenance of topic maps that may be based on a variety of ontologies.
In order to be able to provide the most intuitive possible user
interface for such a generic application, &ted; is
<emphasis>ontology-driven</emphasis>. What this means is that the
forms-based interface for creating and maintaining a topic map is
generated automatically from the underlying ontology and the rules that
are defined for it.</para>

<para>For this reason, you need to create an ontology before you can
edit a topic map instance in &ted;. Often the tasks of creating the
ontology and editing the topic map instance (that is, populating the
ontology) will be carried out by different people. &ted; is therefore
divided into two main parts: the ontology editor and the instance
editor. The application also has an administration interface, i.e., a
page for adding metadata to the topic map (description, creator,
version, etc.), validating it, etc.; and an interface for exporting to
various interchange syntaxes.</para>

<para>The Topic Map Index Page allows you to open an existing topic map, create
a new one, or import one from outside &ted;. Once you have selected one
of these actions, you are taken to the application pages. The overall
architecture and the navigation paths between the various parts of the
application are shown in <xref linkend="int-ovr"/>.</para>

<figure id="int-ovr">
<title>Overview of &ted;&#8217;s architecture</title>
<graphic fileref="images/interface_overview.png"/>
</figure>
</section>

<section id="components">
<title>Configuring and populating topic maps</title>

<para>&ted;&#8217;s two primary functions provide a comprehensive Topic Maps
editing environment.</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Configuring a topic map</emphasis>: ontology
and schema creation</para>
<para>&ted;&#8217;s Type Configuration Pages are used by the ontology
designer to define the topic, name, association, association role, and
occurrence types that will be available to creators of the instance
topics. To take an example, when an author creates a topic of type
<emphasis>composer</emphasis>, the Instance Editing Page will show the
fields that apply to a <emphasis>composer</emphasis>, such as name, date
of birth, and works; but when editing an <emphasis>opera</emphasis>, the
fields will be different.</para>
<para>As the ontology designer assigns fields (such as associations and
occurrences) to a topic type, the designer is also creating the schema.
The creation of the ontology and the schema are seamless and appear to
the designer as a cohesive operation. For further detail on ontology
creation, see <xref linkend="OE"/>.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Populating a topic map</emphasis>: instance
creation</para>
<para>Once an ontology is created, it can be used to guide populating
the topic map. The Instance Editing Pages are used by the person
authoring the topic map instance. The available topic types are provided
from the ontology. The schema constraints give the instance author
further support by allowing only specific association types and
occurrence types to be used with an instance of a given topic type. For
further detail on instance editing, see <xref linkend="IE"/>.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

</section>

<section>
<title>User interface conventions</title>

<para>&ted; has a web-based interface. For a discussion of the various
areas of the &ted; interface and a complete list of icons, tabs and
buttons used in the interface, please see <ulink url="#appA">Appendix
A</ulink>.</para>
</section>

<section id="start-page">
<title>Topic Map Index Page</title>

<para>Before you can create either the ontology or the instance, you
have to open a topic map, so let&#8217;s start there.</para>

<para>When you first access &ted; from &ots;, you are taken to the
Topic Map Index Page, see <xref linkend="wel-pg-fig"/>. On the left, is a column
for <guilabel>Ontopoly Topic Maps</guilabel>, in the middle is the list
of <guilabel>Other Topic Maps</guilabel> (also referred to as
&#8220;non-&ted; topic maps&#8221;), and on the right is the area for
creating new topic maps. Another column, <guilabel>Missing Topic
Maps</guilabel>, will also appear on this page if an &ted; topic map has
been deleted from outside &ted;. For more information on deleting &ted;
topic maps, please see <xref linkend="del-tm"/>.</para>

<figure id="wel-pg-fig">
<title>&ted; Topic Map Index Page</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_welcome_page.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>&ted; imports topic maps in the XTM 1.0 and 2.0, CTM, LTM, and
TM/XML syntaxes; it will also import RDF. By default &ted; creates
topic maps as XTM files in the Omnigator&#8217;s
<filename>topicmaps/</filename> directory. For information on
exporting from &ted;, see <xref linkend="export"/>.</para>

<section id="open-topicmap">
<title>&ted; topic maps</title>

<para>A topic map created in &ted; (an <firstterm>&ted; topic
map</firstterm>) will differ from one created outside of it (a
<firstterm>non-&ted; topic map</firstterm>). An &ted; topic map carries
along with it topics that let it interact with the &ted; application and
topics that define the schema (the <firstterm>system
topics</firstterm>). You can always export a topic map from &ted; to
remove the system topics, but they are needed for the topic map to be
understood within the application. (It&#8217;s the system topics that
make it possible for &ted; to automatically configure its instance
editor for maximum ease of use.) Similarly, pre-existing non-&ted; topic
maps will need these system topics to be added. &ted; automatically adds
them when opening a non-&ted; topic map.</para>

<para>In the situation where you are trying to load an Ontopoly topic
map using an older versjon of the ontology, you will be forward to an
upgrade page. If you want to perform the upgrade click the
<guilabel>OK</guilabel> button. Otherwise click
<guilabel>Cancel</guilabel>. Once the upgrade is done you will be
forwarded to the Type Type Index Page.</para>

<figure id="open-topicmap-upgrade">
<title>Conversion page</title>
<graphic fileref="images/open-topicmap-upgrade.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

</section>

<section id="open-non-topicmap">
<title>Opening a non-&ted; topic map</title>

<para>If you try to open a non-&ted; topic map, you will be forwarded
to the conversion page, which looks something like this:</para>

<figure id="open-topicmap-convert">
<title>Conversion page</title>
<graphic fileref="images/open-topicmap-convert.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>Opening a non-&ted; topic map converts it to an &ted; topic map
and creates an index in the process (which may take several minutes).
When you click on a non-&ted; topic map, you will get information
about the conversion process. If the topic map contains features not
supported by &ted; (see <xref linkend="appB"/>), you will see a
warning and a list of the unsupported features that are used in the
topic map. There are options to update your existing topic map or
create a copy of it. After this decision, you are taken to the Topic
Type Configuration Page.</para>

<para>During the conversion, &ted; makes decisions about the ontology,
based on what it finds in the topic map, and generates the strictest
possible schema. Sometimes it will be stricter than necessary. For
example, if occurrences of a particular type (say,
<emphasis>email</emphasis>) never occur more than once for any
<emphasis>person</emphasis> topic, then &ted; may create a rule allowing
a maximum of one <emphasis>email</emphasis> occurrence per
<emphasis>person</emphasis> topic. You may want to relax the rule,
however, using &ted;&#8217;s ontology editor, in order to allow for the
possibility of multiple <emphasis>email</emphasis> occurrences in the
future. For this reason you should always examine the ontology generated
by &ted; when importing an external topic map, and adjust it to reflect
the true intent behind the topic map.</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Creating a new &ted; topic map</title>

<para>Use the <emphasis>Name</emphasis> field in the right hand column of
the page to create a new topic map. After naming the topic map, you are
taken to the Topic Type Configuration Page. The name you enter will be
used for the name of the topic map and will appear in the left-hand
column on the Topic Map Index Page when subsequently accessed. (You will be able to change it later, if you
like, see <xref linkend="topic-map-config"/>.) The name will also be
used to generate a file name, with the extension
<filename>.xtm</filename> being added automatically.</para>

<!-- TODO: add description of what happens when one can create RDBMS topic maps as well. -->

</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Our example topic map</title>

<para>A simple topic map example will be used throughout the next two
sections to illustrate &ted;&#8217;s functionality. It is a topic map
that captures information about artists, the albums they have made, and
tracks on the album. We've called it <citetitle>Jill&#8217;s
Music</citetitle> and it&#8217;s based on an ontology called
<citetitle>MyMusic</citetitle>; both are included in the Ontopoly
distribution.</para>

<para>So, why wait? Go on now to section <xref linkend="OE"/> and start
creating your first topic map in &ted;!</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="OE">
<title>Using the Type Configuration Pages</title>


<para>Each topic map you create will be about some domain of knowledge,
such as your corporate intranet, medical research, recording artists,
the works of Shakespeare, etc. A topic map identifies subjects and the
relationships between those subjects. Each of the subjects will be of a
certain type, e.g., Puccini and Verdi are composers, La Scala and Fenice
are opera houses, Milan and Venice are cities, etc.</para>

<para>Using &ted;&#8217;s Type Configuration Pages, you will create the
<firstterm>typing topics</firstterm> that will control your topic map: topic,
association, occurrence, role and name types. You will also create the rules
for how the typing topics are used together.</para>

<para>To provide a practical introduction to &ted;&#8217;s
functionality, we&#8217;ve created an ontology for a music organization
topic map, <citetitle>MyMusic</citetitle>, and an example topic map that
uses that ontology, <citetitle>Jill&#8217;s Music</citetitle>.</para>

<para>Here are the topic types we will be working with:</para>

<blockquote>
<literallayout>Album
Artist
   Group
   Individual Artist
Track</literallayout>
</blockquote>

<para>The indentation indicates that Group and Individual Artist are subtypes
(or subclasses) of Artist.</para>

<para>In addition, we have defined the following association
types:</para>

<blockquote>
<literallayout>Album created by
Belongs to album
Is a Member of</literallayout>
</blockquote>

<section id="onto-indexes">
<title>Type Index Pages</title>

<para>When you open an existing or newly created topic map, you are
taken to the Topic Type Index Page, see <xref linkend="tt1"/>. Here
you&#8217;ll see menu buttons for each kind of typing topic: topic
types, occurrence types, association types, role types, and name types.
The <emphasis role="bold">Ontology</emphasis> tab is available on every
page in &ted;. Clicking on it will always bring you to the Topic Type
Index Page. From there you can quickly access the corresponding Type
Index Pages for other kinds of typing topics, which are typically used
less often.</para>

<para>All of the Type Index Pages are more-or-less the same. Each one
presents a tree of existing types and a field for creating a new type.
The types are displayed as a type hierarchy and includes buttons for
expanding and collapsing the tree structure.</para>

<para>Clicking on any of the typing topics (or creating a new one) takes
you to the appropriate Configuration Page, as described below.</para>

<figure id="tt1">
<title>Topic Type Index Page</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_onto_topic_types_1.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>Creating an ontology is an iterative process. Through
&ted;&#8217;s interface, you can navigate easily between the Type Index
Pages and the Type Configuration Pages. In the following we describe
each kind of Type Configuration Page in turn, but in your work you will
find yourself moving back and forth throughout the process.</para>

</section>
<section id="config-pages">
<title>Type Configuration Pages</title>
<para>There are five kinds of types in Topic Maps: topic types,
occurrence types, association types, role types, and name types. Each
of these has its own kind of Type Configuration Page, which is
accessed via the links at the top on the Type Index Pages. Each Type
Configuration Page is unique, but some fields are common to all of
them (see <xref linkend="tt-config-1"/>):</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem id="tt-config-name">
<para><guilabel>Name</guilabel>: Editable name of the typing
topic.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem id="tt-config-PSI">
<para><guilabel>Subject identifier</guilabel>: The (Published) Subject
Identifier of the typing topic. Its value must be a URI. The
&add-field; icon following this field indicates that you can create
more than one. A subject identifier is not required, but is good
practice. For more information on using PSIs, please see the <ulink
url="http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/download.php/3050/pubsubj-pt1-1.02-cs.pdf">OASIS
Recommendations</ulink>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem id="tt-config-description">
<para><guilabel>Description</guilabel>: Field for defining and
documenting the topic type. We recommend that you use this field
extensively to capture your intentions regarding the role of this type
in your ontology.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>The following two fields appear on the Advanced view panel for
all types:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem id="tt-config-read-only">
<para><guilabel>Read-only</guilabel>: You may create typing topics that
can only be read. The instance author will be able to choose such a
topic type and read what is in it, but no instances may be
created.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem id="tt-config-hidden">
<para><guilabel>Hidden</guilabel>: In some cases topic types should only
be seen by the ontology designer, and that&#8217;s the perfect use of
this choice as the topic will not be available in the instance
editor.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>The following sections provide more detail on each kind of Type
Configuration Page.</para>
</section>

<section id="create-tt">
<title>Configuring topic types</title>
<para>The Topic Type Index is shown in <xref linkend="tt1"/>. From here
you can enter a name for a new topic type in the field and then click
<guibutton>Create</guibutton>, or you can choose an existing topic type
to view or edit. Our example already contains an ontology which has been
partially populated, so we will go straight to the Topic Type
Configuration Page for a pre-existing type,
<emphasis>Artist</emphasis>.</para>

<section id="tt-config-page">
<title>Topic Type Configuration Page</title>
<para>Configuration pages control what the instance authors will see as
they create topics of a given type. Let&#8217;s look at the Topic Type
Configuration Page in <xref linkend="tt-config-1"/>. <!-- Some standard
components appear that are available on all pages. The page type
(&#8220;Topic Type Configuration&#8221;) appears at the end of the
Breadcrumbs, and the topic type being created
(<emphasis>Artist</emphasis>) is just above that in red.--></para>

<para>The main portion of the page is divided into three parts: the
top part lists the core properties of the typing topic (its name,
subject identifier and description fields plus abstract, superclass
and subclass fields which are specific to topic types); the lower part
of the page lists those properties, or &#8220;fields&#8221; (i.e.,
names, identifiers, occurrences, and associations), that will apply to
instances of the type; the right part contains operations, that can be
performed on the topic type, and links to other relevant pages.</para>

<para>The properties that are common to all typing topics and thus
occur on all Configuration Pages were described above in <xref
linkend="config-pages"/>. This applies to <guilabel>Name</guilabel>,
<guilabel>Subject identifier</guilabel>,
<guilabel>Description</guilabel>, <guilabel>Read-only</guilabel>, and
<guilabel>Hidden</guilabel>. The first three fields are shown in the
Default view panel and the last two on the Advanced view panel. The
following additional properties are specific to topic types:</para>
</section>

<section id="tt-config-standard-default">
<title>Properties of the typing topic (Default view panel)</title>

<figure id="tt-config-1">
<title>Topic Type Configuration Page - default properties</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_topic_types_config.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem id="tt-config-abstract">
<para><guilabel>Abstract</guilabel>: Check this box if you
want to use this typing topic as a model for other topics, but don't
want a user to create any instances of it directly. Typically, an
abstract topic will be a supertype in a hierarchy of topics. In our
example, we have a two-tier hierarchy where <emphasis>Artist</emphasis> is
the supertype and <emphasis>Individual Artist</emphasis> and
<emphasis>Group</emphasis> are subtypes. We will not want authors to
create instances of <emphasis>Artist</emphasis>, only of its subtypes.
However, having the <emphasis>Artist</emphasis> supertype is useful
because, once we define it, its subtypes will inherit all of its fields.
If one subtype requires fields not needed by the other subtypes, those
fields can be added at subtype level.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem id="tt-config-supertype">
<para><guilabel>Superclass</guilabel>: A drop down list of topics from
which to choose a supertype (i.e., a parent in the type hierarchy) for
the current topic. (In our example there is no supertype, because
<emphasis>Artist</emphasis> is at the top of the hierarchy and thus has no
parent.)</para>
</listitem>

<listitem id="tt-config-subtype">
<para><guilabel>Subclass</guilabel>: A list of topics of which
this topic is the supertype (i.e., parent in the type hierarchy). In our
example, although <emphasis>Artist</emphasis> has no supertype, it does
have two subtypes, each of which is highlighted as a link that can take
you to the corresponding Type Configuration Page. After the last
subtype, there is a &create; icon that can be used to create another
topic type which will automatically become a subtype of the current
topic type.</para>

<para>Note that the type hierarchy can be constructed from two
directions: upwards (by assigning the supertype of each topic type), or
downwards (by specifying its subtypes). You can also use a combination
of the two approaches. This hierarchy can be made visible on the Topic
Type Index Page by clicking on <guilabel>Expand all nodes</guilabel>
(see <xref linkend="tt1"/>).</para>
</listitem>

<!--listitem id="tt-config-role-type">
<para><guilabel>Use as role type</guilabel>: If you would like to use
this topic not only as a topic type, but also as a role type in
associations (see <xref linkend="assoc-types"/> and <xref
linkend="role-types"/>), you can check this box, rather than create a
separate role type. In our example, we want to use
<emphasis>Artist</emphasis> as a role type in associations of type
&#8220;Album created by&#8221;, so this box is checked.</para>
</listitem-->
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section id="tt-config-standard-advanced">
<title>Properties of the typing topic (Advanced view panel)</title>

<figure id="tt-config-2">
<title>Topic Type Configuration Page - advanced properties</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_topic_types_config_advanced.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Large instance set</guilabel>: Some topic types have
such a large set of instances that you do not want the user to be able
to display the entire list, because this would take too long to
render, and the pages would be too big. Checking this box makes
Ontopoly turn off the listing feature, and would require the user to
search for instance topics instead.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Hierarchical associations</guilabel>: Here you can
select a number of association types that together form a hierarchy of
the instances of this topic type. The only association types which can
be selected here are those which on the Association Type Configuration
Page (see <xref linkend="at-config-page"/>) are defined as being
hierarchical. The effect of this setting is to get topics of this type
presented in a tree view on the Instance Index Page (see <xref
linkend="inst-index"/>) and in the Topic Selection Dialog (see <xref
linkend="topic-select-dialog"/>).</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Hierarchy definition query</guilabel>: Sometimes you
will want to define your own hierarchy for the instances of a topic
type without using the default hierarchy pattern. For those situations
you can specify a tolog query that retrieves the preferred
hierarchy. The query should return two columns, which contains all the
parent/child combinations in the hierarchy/tree. The first column must
contain the parents and the second column must contain the
children. Topics with no parents and no children must return null in
the parent column and itself in the child column. The query should
also sort first by the parent column and then by the child column. The
query can take one parameter, <parameter>%topicType%</parameter>,
which is the topic type itself. There are no restrictions on the
column names. <remark>This is not yet supported.</remark></para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section id="tt-config-fields-editor">
<title>Assigning new fields</title>

<figure id="fig-tt-config-fields-editor">
<title>Topic Type Configuration Page - default properties</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_topic_types_fields_editor.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>In the lower part of the Topic Type Configuration Page (in the
default view) you can define and add fields to the topic for use in
the Instance Editing Pages. The fields shown here are the fields that
are already assigned to the topic type. The
<guilabel>Names</guilabel>, <guilabel>Occurrences</guilabel>,
<guilabel>Associations</guilabel>, and <guilabel>Identities</guilabel>
links at the top will allow you to assign new fields and the &create;
icon will let you create a new field by creating a new ontology
type. New fields will be placed at the bottom of the fields
list.</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem id="tt-config-add-fields-name">
<para><guilabel>Names</guilabel>: Clicking this label will display a
list of available name types on the right side. From this list you can
assign a new field for the given name type by clicking the
&assign-field; icon. Only name types not already assigned to this
topic type will be shown in the list. By default, there is just one
name type: <emphasis>Name</emphasis>, which is for general-purpose,
&#8220;untyped&#8221; names. In our sample topic map the
<emphasis>Name</emphasis> name is already assigned, but we get another
name <emphasis>Nickname</emphasis> that we can assign from the
list.</para>

<para>You can create new name types by clicking the &create;
icon. This will also assign a new name field and then take you to the
Name Type Configuration Page, see <xref linkend="name-types"/>.</para>

<figure id="fig-tt-config-fields-editor-names">
<graphic fileref="images/doc_topic_types_fields_editor_names.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>
</listitem>

<listitem id="tt-config-add-fields-occurrence">
<para><guilabel>Occurrences</guilabel>: Clicking this label will
display a list of available occurrence types on the right side. From
this list you can assign a new field for the given occurrence type by
clicking the &assign-field; icon. Only occurrence types not already
assigned to this topic type will be shown in the list. By default,
there are three predefined occurrence types:
<emphasis>Creator</emphasis>, <emphasis>Description</emphasis>, and
<emphasis>Version</emphasis>. In our sample topic map only
<emphasis>Creator</emphasis> and <emphasis>Version</emphasis> shows up
in the list as <emphasis>Description</emphasis> has already been
assigned.</para>

<para>You can create new occurrence types by clicking the &create;
icon. This will also assign a new occurrence field and then take you
to the Occurrence Type Configuration Page, see <xref
linkend="occur-types"/>.</para>

<figure id="fig-tt-config-fields-editor-occurrences">
<graphic fileref="images/doc_topic_types_fields_editor_occurrences.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>
</listitem>

<listitem id="tt-config-add-fields-association">
<para><guilabel>Associations</guilabel>: Clicking this label will
display a list of available association types on the right side. The
list will also show information about what kind of topic can be found
at the other end of the associations. From this list you can assign a
new field for the given association type by clicking the
&assign-field; icon. Only association types not already assigned to
this topic type will be shown in the list. By default there are no
predefined association types. In our sample topic map
<emphasis>Belongs to album</emphasis>, <emphasis>Created
album</emphasis>, <emphasis>Has/had as Members</emphasis> and
<emphasis>Is/was a Member of</emphasis> shows up in the
list. <emphasis>Contains track</emphasis> and <emphasis>Album created
by</emphasis> has already been assigned.</para>

<para>You can create new association types by clicking the &create;
icon. This will also assign a new role field and an association field
and then take you to the Association Type Configuration Page, see <xref
linkend="assoc-types"/>.</para>

<para>In the case where a topic might play both roles, such as
<emphasis>parent</emphasis> and <emphasis>child</emphasis> in a
<emphasis>parent-child</emphasis> association, each role (field) should
be selected in turn so that both are available fields on the Instance
Editing Page.</para>

<figure id="fig-tt-config-fields-editor-associations">
<graphic fileref="images/doc_topic_types_fields_editor_associations.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>
</listitem>

<listitem id="tt-config-add-fields-identity">
<para><guilabel>Identities</guilabel>: Clicking this label will
display a list of available identity types on the right side. From
this list you can assign a new field for the given identity type by
clicking the &assign-field; icon. Only identity types not already
assigned to this topic type will be shown in the list. By default,
there are three predefined identity types: <emphasis>Subject
identifier</emphasis>, <emphasis>Subject locator</emphasis>, and
<emphasis>Item identifier</emphasis>. In our sample topic map only
<emphasis>Subject locator</emphasis> and <emphasis>Item
identifier</emphasis> shows up in the list as <emphasis>Subject
identifier</emphasis> has already been assigned.</para>

<para>You cannot create new identity types at this time.</para>

<para>If topics of this type represent information resources (which
would probably be the case for the topic type
<emphasis>Document</emphasis>, for example), the type can be assigned a
<emphasis>Subject locator</emphasis> field, otherwise the type can
(and, in many cases, should) be assigned a <emphasis>Subject
identifier</emphasis> field. For more information on the use of
subject identifiers and subject locators, see the <ulink
url="http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/download.php/3050/pubsubj-pt1-1.02-cs.pdf">OASIS
Recommendations</ulink>.</para>

<!-- TODO: Add description of what item identifiers are -->

<figure id="fig-tt-config-fields-editor-identities">
<graphic fileref="images/doc_topic_types_fields_editor_identities.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</section>
<section id="tt-config-existing-fields">
<title>Editing existing fields</title>
<para>Now let&#8217;s move on down to the existing fields. As you can
see from the figure below the <emphasis>Artist</emphasis> topic type has
five fields assigned. Each field is displayed in a separate table
row.</para>

<figure id="fig-tt-config-fields-editor-existing">
<graphic fileref="images/doc_topic_types_fields_editor_existing.png" width="50%"/>
</figure>

<para>At the left you find the &dnd; icon. Use this icon to reorder
the fields. Drag the icon on top of the field that you want the
dragged field to be ordered after. Note that in order to make a field
become the first field you have to first drag it on top of the first
field and then afterwards drag the first field on top of the new
second field.</para>

<para>The &goto-details; icon will let you edit the topic that
represents the field. Clicking this icon will navigate to the instance
page of the field. This page will reveal more detailed information
about the field.</para>

<para>Next is the field label. The label is a link that lets you
navigate to the name type, occurrence type, association type or
identity type topics declared by the field.</para>

<para>To the right of the field label is the value type of the
field. This will tell you what kind of values can be assigned to this
field. In our example the <emphasis>Name</emphasis> is a name string,
the <emphasis>Subject identifier</emphasis> is a URI, and the
<emphasis>Description</emphasis> is a string. The association fields
shows the kind of topics that can be associated through the field. The
<emphasis>Contains track</emphasis> can contain
<emphasis>Track</emphasis>s and the <emphasis>Album created
by</emphasis> can contain <emphasis>Artist</emphasis>s. If the value
type is <emphasis>Many</emphasis> then multiple topic types can be
associated through that field. Hold the mouse over the
<emphasis>Many</emphasis> label to see which topic types that
is.</para>

<para>The drop-down list shows the cardinality choices for the number
of times the field can or must be used in the Instance Editing
Page. There are four possible choices: <emphasis>Exactly
one</emphasis>, <emphasis>One or more</emphasis>, <emphasis>Zero or
more</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Zero or one</emphasis>.</para>

<para>Each line ends with the &remove-field; icon, which is used to
remove fields, i.e. unassign them. Removing a field will make it once
more available as a option to reassign. If the icon is shown
instead of the remove icon then it means that the field has been
assigned to a supertype. Clicking the icon will navigate to the
supertype that declares the field. The field can then be removed there
instead.</para>

<para>We now know how to add fields to a topic type. However, most of
these fields have to be defined by the ontology designer through the use
of the other Configuration Pages, so let&#8217;s move on.</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="occur-types">
<title>Configuring occurrence types</title>
<para>Occurrences can refer to resources external to the topic map, such
as a web page, or they can be internal to the topic map, in which case
they can be thought of as attributes (or properties) of the subject that
the topic represents. You can create new occurrence types or choose one
for edit from the Occurrence Type Index, see <xref linkend="ot1"/>,
which will take you to the Occurrence Type Configuration Page, see <xref
linkend="occur-config-page-1"/>.</para>

<figure id="ot1">
<title>Occurrence Type Index Page</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_onto_occur_types.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<section id="ot-config-page">
<title>Occurrence Type Configuration Page</title>

<para>The Occurrence Type Configuration Page for
<emphasis>Description</emphasis> looks as follows:</para>

<figure id="occur-config-page-1">
<title>Occurrence Type Configuration Page - default properties</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_occur_config_1.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>The core properties of the occurrence type topic are shown in
the upper part of the page; the lower part contains the information
about how fields of this type will be used when editing instances. The
properties of the occurrence field is displayed in the grey
<guilabel>Occurrence field</guilabel> field box. This box represents
the field that is assigned to topic types. The actual topic types that
is assigned the field (and indirectly the occurrence type) can be seen
in the <guilabel>Used by</guilabel> field.</para>

<para>Core properties common to all typing topics are described in
<xref linkend="config-pages"/>.</para>
</section>

<section id="occur-config-standard">
<title>Properties of the occurrence field (Default view panel)</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Name</guilabel>: This is the name of the field. The
value will be used to display the label of the field in the user
interface. If no value is given the name of the occurrence type will
be used.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Data type</guilabel>: This field describes the value
type of the occurrence field. The value type can be any of the
following:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>String</guilabel>: a string value (the
default).</para>
<!--Note for more technical doc - there is no max string length. With
the RDBMS backend there may be maximums, but they will depend on the DB
schema.-->
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><emphasis role="bold">URI</emphasis>: a web address.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Date</guilabel>: a date value, matching the
<symbol>YYYY-MM-DD</symbol> pattern. Values can be selected using a
calendar widget.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Datetime</guilabel>: a datetime value, matching the
<symbol>YYYY-MM-DD hh:mm:ss</symbol> pattern. Instance authors are
given a calendar widget.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Number</guilabel>: a numeric value, either an integer
(like <symbol>42</symbol>) or a decimal (like <symbol>-4.2</symbol>),
with an optional negative sign in front.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>HTML</guilabel>: an HTML document or an HTML
fragment. HTML content will be edited using a rich text editor.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Image</guilabel>: an image. Images can be uploaded via
a file upload widget.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Used by</guilabel>: If the occurrence field has been
assigned by any topic types, they are listed here, highlighted as
links to their Configuration Pages.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Cardinality</guilabel>: The field specifies the
cardinality of the field. The cardinality specifies the number of
times the field can or must be used in the Instance Editing
Page. There are four possible choices: <emphasis>Exactly
one</emphasis>, <emphasis>One or more</emphasis>, <emphasis>Zero or
more</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Zero or one</emphasis>. The default is
<emphasis>Zero or more</emphasis>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>As the occurrence fields are ones in which the author will be
providing content rather than picking topic names or role labels, it
is necessary for the ontology designer to describe the dimensions that
the field will be given on the Instance Editing Page. Two fields are
provided for this purpose:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Width</guilabel>: in characters (the default is
50)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Depth</guilabel>: in rows (the default is 1)</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section id="occur-config-standard-advanced">
<title>Properties of the occurrence field (Advanced view panel)</title>

<figure id="occur-config-page-1-advanced">
<title>Occurrence Type Configuration Page - default properties</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_occur_config_1_advanced.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>The occurrence type's Advanced view panel contains only the two
standard <emphasis>Read-only</emphasis> and
<emphasis>Hidden</emphasis> fields.</para>
</section>

</section>

<section id="assoc-types">
<title>Configuring association types</title>

<para>Associations describe a relationship that can or must exist
between topics. You can create new association types or choose one for
edit from the Association Type Index, see <xref linkend="at1"/>, which
will take you to the Association Type Configuration Page, see <xref
linkend="assoc-config-page-1"/></para>

<figure id="at1">
<title>Association Type Index Page</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_onto_assoc_types_1.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>
<para>Most associations are binary, that is, there are two role
players, such as in parent-child or employer-employee
relationships. You can also create associations with only one role
player, or with three or more role players. We will focus on binary
associations for the scope of this document.</para>

<para>Binary associations are bi-directional. For example, an association
named <emphasis>composed-by</emphasis> might sound like it is only
uni-directional, i.e., Tosca is composed by Puccini. However, it also
represents the relationship expressed as, for example, Puccini composed
Tosca. Topic Maps accomplishes this bi-directionality, unambiguously, by
assigning roles to the players. The relationship expressed in
<xref linkend="assoc-bidirectional"/> can be described as, &#8220;In the
composed-by relationship, the role of composer is played by Puccini and
the role of work is played by Tosca.&#8221;</para>

<!--
<note>
<para>Even though the relationship is bi-directional, the number of
times each role player can use the relationship, i.e., the cardinality,
can be set individually from the Topic Type Configuration Page for each
role player.</para>
</note>
-->

<figure id="assoc-bidirectional">
<title>Associations are bi-directional</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_assoc_bidirectional.png"/>
</figure>
<para>&ted;&#8217;s Association Type Configuration Page helps you to
define the association type, roles their role types and their
corresponding role player types, and the labels for role fields as
seen from the perspective of each role player.</para>

<section id="at-config-page">
<title>Association Type Configuration Page</title>

<para>The Association Type Configuration Page for
<emphasis>Album created by</emphasis> looks as follows:</para>

<figure id="assoc-config-page-1">
<title>Association Type Configuration Page - default properties</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_assoc_config_1.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>The core properties of the association type are again shown in
the upper part of the page; the lower part contains information
relating to the role fields declared for the associaion type.</para>

<para>Core properties common to all typing topics are described in
<xref linkend="config-pages"/>.</para>
</section>

<section id="assoc-config-standard">
<title>Properties of the typing topic (Default view panel)</title>

<para>The Association Type Configuration Page contains one new
checkbox in the top portion of the form,
<guilabel>Symmetric</guilabel>, and an association field labelled
<guilabel>Association field</guilabel>.</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Symmetric</guilabel>: A symmetric relation is one
which is the same from both (or all) directions. The teacher/pupil
relation is not symmetric, because the two participants are doing
different things, whereas the is-neighbour relation is symmetric,
since there&#8217;s no difference between the two neighbours. In one
sense, you can say the participants in a symmetric relationship are
equal, which does not hold for created-by, killed-by, eaten-by, but
does hold for works-with, is-a-friend-of, is-a-sibling-of,
is-the-spouse-of, etc.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Association field</guilabel>: This is the relation
between the association type and its association fields. Inside each
association field, of which there is normally only one, there is
another field called <guilabel>Roles</guilabel> that references the
individual role fields. The role field box represents the field that
is assigned to topic types. The actual topic types that is assigned
the field (and indirectly the role type and association type) can be
seen in the Used by field. In our example the association type has one
association field which has two role fields.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<section id="assoc-config-roles">
<title>Roles</title>

<para>In general, there is one role box for each role player. In most
cases, there will be two role players and therefore two role boxes. In
symmetric associations (and unary associations), there is only one role
box. It is also possible to have more than two role players (in what are
known as &#8220;n-ary associations&#8221;); an example of a ternary
association (one with three role players) would be a perpetrator, a
victim, and a cause of death in a "killed / killed-by"
association.</para>

<para>Each role box has four fields:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Name</guilabel>: You can define a string as the label
that will be seen from the perspective of this role. For example, in a
parent-child relationship, from the perspective of the parent role, the
label might be "is the parent of", while from the perspective of the
child role, the label would be "is the child of".</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Role type</guilabel>: The values available in the drop-down
correlate to role type topics. You can create new role types directly
from this page by using the &create; icon, which will take you to a new
Role Type Configuration Page, see <xref linkend="role-types"/>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Used by</guilabel>: Use the drop-down list to
choose the appropriate topic type to play this role. Note that this is a
repeatable field as multiple topic types may play the same role. New
topic types can be created directly from this page using the &create;
icon. Once you choose <guilabel>Confirm</guilabel>, the drop-down box is
replaced by a link to the chosen topic type. The &add-field; icon
generates another drop-down box for additional choices.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Cardinality</guilabel>: The field specifies the
cardinality of the field. The cardinality specifies the number of
times the field can or must be used in the Instance Editing
Page. There are four possible choices: <emphasis>Exactly
one</emphasis>, <emphasis>One or more</emphasis>, <emphasis>Zero or
more</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Zero or one</emphasis>. The default is
<emphasis>Zero or more</emphasis>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Interface control</guilabel>: Choose between providing
instance authors with a drop-down list of valid topic types, or a search
box, or a browse window, or an auto-complete input field.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Once you have created an association type, visit the Topic Type
Configuration Pages of the topics that play roles to make sure the
cardinality for the use of the association is correct. These should be
reviewed from the perspective of each role player as they may differ,
e.g., a student goes to one school (<emphasis>Exactly one</emphasis>), but
a school may have many students (<emphasis>One or more</emphasis>).</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="assoc-config-standard-advanced">
<title>Properties of the typing topic (Advanced view panel)</title>

<figure id="assoc-config-page-1-advanced">
<title>Association Type Configuration Page - advanced properties</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_assoc_config_1_advanced.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>
This section allows you to configure an association type as being
hierarchical. To do this, you must also set the role types correctly,
so that Ontopoly knows which role is the parent role and which is the
child role. The purpose of this to enable Ontopoly to show you the
hierarchy formed by these associations. 
</para>

<para>
An example might be the hierarchy formed by the geographical
"contained in" association. The parent role here would be "container"
and the child role would be "containee". Setting this up would allow
you to browse your collection of geographic places as a tree on the
Instance Index Page (see <xref linkend="inst-index"/>) and in the
Topic Selection Dialog (see <xref linkend="topic-select-dialog"/>).
Another example might be the broader/narrower relationship from
taxonomies and thesauri, which you can find in the UK Government
Category List, which comes with Ontopoly.
</para>

<para>Note that to register an association type as hierarchical one
must add the <emphasis>Hierarchical Relation Type</emphasis> topic
type to the association type. At the moment this can only be done in
Administrator mode, and using the <guilabel>Add or remove topic
type</guilabel> action item on the right side of the page.
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Superordinate for</guilabel>: Here you specify
the role type that is the parent role.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Subordinate for</guilabel>: Here you specify the
role type that is the child role.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Hierarchical for</guilabel>: Not all players should be
part of a hierarchy, so here you can specify the topic types for which
this associaion type should be considered hierarchical.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</section>
</section>

<section id="role-types">
<title>Configuring role types</title>

<para>Role types are used in associations to represent the semantics
of why a topic participates in an association. For role types one
either selects an existing topic type (e.g. "opera") or one creates a
topic that represents a more specific role (e.g. "composer"),
i.e. something that describes what it means for a topic to be part of
the role. As you can see one might choose a role type that represents
what the player does as opposed to what the person inherently
is. Beethoven is a person, but he is also composer because he composed
something. Topic types should be universally valid for the topic. Role
types on the other hand can, and often should, be more context
dependent. Role types should be as generic as possible so that they
can easily be reused across association types. For example, whether
you have a "composer/opera", "author/book", or "artist/painting"
association, the roles the topics play in all three of these examples
might be "creator" and "creation", even though the association types
could be different.</para>

<para>You can create new role types or choose one for edit from the
Role Type Index page, see <xref linkend="rt1"/>, which will take you
to the Role Type Configuration Page, see <xref
linkend="role-config-page-1"/>. </para>

<figure id="rt1">
<title>Role Type Index Page</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_onto_role_types_1.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<section id="rt-config-page">
<title>Role Type Configuration Page</title>

<para>In our sample topic map there is only one topic,
<emphasis>Member</emphasis>, that is specifically registered as a role
type. All other role types used in the topic map are topic types. The
Role Type Configuration Page for <emphasis>Member</emphasis> looks as
follows:</para>

<figure id="role-config-page-1">
<title>Role Type Configuration Page - default properties</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_role_config_1.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>Core properties common to all typing topics are described in
<xref linkend="config-pages"/>.</para>
</section>

<section id="role-config-standard">
<title>Properties of the typing topic (Default view panel)</title>
<para>There are not really any new properties here. The first three
are core properties common to all typing topics. The <guilabel>Role
field</guilabel> represents the relation between the role type and the
role fields in which it has been declared. The properties of the role
field we have already seen in <xref
linkend="assoc-config-roles"/>.</para>
</section>

<section id="role-config-advanced">
<title>Properties of the typing topic (Advanced view panel)</title>

<figure id="role-config-page-1-advanced">
<title>Role Type Configuration Page - advanced properties</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_role_config_1_advanced.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>The two new fields on this page are the inverse of the
<guilabel>Superordinate role type</guilabel> and <guilabel>Subordinate
role type</guilabel> fields we saw in <xref
linkend="assoc-config-standard-advanced"/>.</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Superordinate role type for</guilabel>: Here you specify
the association type for which this role type is the parent role.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Subordinate role type for</guilabel>: Here you specify the
association type for which this role type is the child role.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</section>
</section>
<section id="name-types">
<title>Configuring name types</title>
<para>Name types are used to define the names of topics in various
contexts. Frequently used name types include <emphasis
role="bold">nickname</emphasis> and <emphasis
role="bold">short</emphasis>, but one of the most popular uses is to
provide the name of the topic in multiple languages. You can create new
name types or choose one for edit from the Name Type Index, see <xref
linkend="nt1"/>, which will take you to the Name Type Configuration
Page, see <xref linkend="name-config-page-1"/></para>

<figure id="nt1">
<title>Name Type Index Page</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_onto_name_types_1.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<section id="nt-config-page">
<title>Name Type Configuration Page (Default view panel)</title>

<para>The Name Type Configuration Page for
<emphasis>Nickname</emphasis> looks as follows:</para>

<figure id="name-config-page-1">
<title>Name Type Configuration Page - default properties</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_name_config_1.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>
<para>Core properties common to all typing topics are described in
<xref linkend="config-pages"/>.</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Name</guilabel>: This is the name of the field. The
value will be used to display the label of the field in the user
interface. If no value is given the name of the name type will
be used.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Used by</guilabel>: If the name field has been
assigned by any topic types, they are listed here, highlighted as
links to their Configuration Pages.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Cardinality</guilabel>: The field specifies the
cardinality of the field. The cardinality specifies the number of
times the field can or must be used in the Instance Editing
Page. There are four possible choices: <emphasis>Exactly
one</emphasis>, <emphasis>One or more</emphasis>, <emphasis>Zero or
more</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Zero or one</emphasis>. The default is
<emphasis>Zero or more</emphasis>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section id="nt-config-page-advanced">
<title>Name Type Configuration Page (Advanced view panel)</title>

<figure id="name-config-page-1-advanced">
<title>Name Type Configuration Page - default properties</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_name_config_1_advanced.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>There are no new properties in the advanced view outside of the
core commmon properties described in <xref
linkend="config-pages"/>.</para>
</section>

</section>

<section id="topic-map-config">
<title>Topic Map Description Page</title>

<para>Once you are within a topic map, you can choose to enter
descriptive information about it. Use the
<guilabel>Description</guilabel> tab to access the Description Page (see
<xref linkend="config"/>).</para>

<para>This page can be used to change the name of the topic map, but the
file name will remain the same as assigned when creating it.</para>

<figure id="config">
<title>Topic Map Description Page</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_config_page.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>There are four editable fields:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Name</guilabel>: the name of the topic map</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Description</guilabel>: a description of the topic map
as a whole</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Creator</guilabel>: the person, group, or company
creating the ontology or topic map</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Version</guilabel>: a user-designated version
number</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<!--para>There are also two non-editable fields:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>ID</guilabel> &#8212; the file name</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guilabel>Ontology version</guilabel> &#8212; this refers to the
version of the &ted; system topics ontology.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist-->

<!--section id="valid">
<title>Validating a topic map</title>
<para>The <guibutton>Validation Report</guibutton> button initiates a
validation pass, that is, it checks the topic map instance against the
rules defined in its ontology. The number of errors found, if any, is
reported, along with links to their location and an indication of the
problem, see <xref linkend="val-rpt"/>.</para>

<figure id="val-rpt">
<title>Validation report</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_validation_rpt.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>In this example, <emphasis>Bruce Springsteen</emphasis> is a link to
the Instance Editing Page for a topic that has been found to be invalid,
and <emphasis>Individual Artist</emphasis> is a link to the Topic Type
Configuration Page for the invalid topic. <emphasis>Create
album</emphasis> is the invalid field and the reason is given as being a
&#8220;missing required field&#8221;. To fix this error, an instance
author can add a value for this field. Alternatively, although less
common, an ontology designer might decide that the field was erroneously
given a required cardinality and adjust the rules via the Topic Type
Configuration Page.</para>
</section-->

<section id="del-tm">
<title>Deleting a topic map</title>

<para>The <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> button on the Description Page
removes the topic map from the list of &ted; Topic Maps and physically
removes the file from the disk.</para>

<note>
<para>&ted; keeps track of your &ted; topic maps. Manually deleting an
&ted; topic map from the file system (as opposed to using the
<guibutton>Delete</guibutton> button on the Description Page) will
result in the display of a <guilabel>Missing Topic Maps</guilabel>
column on the Topic Map Index Page. Therefore, it is best practice only to
delete &ted; topic maps through the <guilabel>Delete</guilabel> button
on the <guilabel>Description</guilabel> tab.</para>
</note>

<para>Clicking the <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> button will open up a
confirmation window. Choose <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to delete the
topic map. You will then be taken to the start page (see <xref
linkend="appB"/>). Clicking the <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button
will cancel the operation and close the confirmation window.</para>

<figure id="del-tm-confirm">
<title>Deletion confirmation window</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_config_page_delete_confirm.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

</section>

<section id="enabling-shortcuts">
<title>Enabling shortcuts</title>

<para>The <guibutton>Enable shortcuts</guibutton> action item on
right-hand side of the Description Page (<xref linkend="config"/>)
will enable some useful shortcuts in the user interface. The field
labels in the editing pages will become links. The &goto-details; icon
will let you go directly to the topic that represents the
field. Clicking the field label will navigate to the name type,
occurrence type, association type or identity type topics declared by
the field. You can later disable shortcuts by clicking the button
again.</para>

<para>Here is an example of what an editing page looks like with
shortcuts enabled:</para>

<figure id="enable-shortcuts-topictype">
<title>Topic Type Configuration Page with shortcuts enabled</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_topic_types_config_shortcuts.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

</section>

<section id="ontology-annotation">
<title>Ontology annotation</title>

<para>
The <guibutton>Enable ontology annotation</guibutton> action item on
right-hand side of the Description Page (<xref linkend="config"/>)
turns on ontology annotation, which is a very powerful feature, but
one that can be a little confusing at first. The basic idea is that
the normal Ontopoly (without this feature) allows you to say anything
you want about instance topics, but for typing topics you are pretty
much restricted to names, subject identifiers, and the description
field. This may not sound like much of a problem, but there are a lot
of useful things that can be done if you can annotate your ontology
topics.
</para>

<para>
Generally, ontology annotation enables you to build more dynamic
applications, by moving logic out of your code and into the topic
map. To take a trivial example, imagine building a search page for
your topic map. On this page you'll need to display things like "found
X people", "found Y documents", etc, and to do this you need to
display the plural names of the topic types. You can of course do this
with a big multi-way test (if current topic type is "person", display
"people"). But the easiest way is to make a name type "Plural name"
and to give each topic type such a name.
</para>

<para>
With ontology annotation this is easy. Once you turn ontology
annotation on, the topic types "Topic type", "Association type", etc
show up in the list of topic types. This lets you give them fields in
the same way as normal topic types, and you can edit them in the
normal way.
</para>

<para>This what the Topic Types Index Page looks like with annotation
enabled. The ontology types are displayed in italic.</para>

<figure id="enable-annotation-topictype">
<title>Topic Type Index Page with annotation enabled</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_onto_topic_types_annotation.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

</section>


<section id="administration-mode">
<title>Administration mode</title>

<para>
The <guibutton>Enable administration mode</guibutton> action item on
right-hand side of the Description Page (<xref linkend="config"/>)
turns on admistration mode, which is an extremely powerful feature as
it gives you access to everything in the topic map, including the
Ontopoly model itself.
</para>

<warning><para>Be careful when using this feature.</para></warning>

<para>As you can see there is a lot of new topic types visible on the
Topic Types Index Page when administration mode is enabled:</para>

<figure id="enable-administration-topictype">
<title>Topic Type Index Page with administration mode enabled</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_onto_topic_types_administration.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

</section>

</section>

<section id="export">
<title>Exporting a topic map</title>

<para>The Export Page (see <xref linkend="export-page"/>) is accessed
via the <guilabel>Admin</guilabel> tab. The desired export format
(LTM, XTM 1.0, XTM 2.0, or RDF) is chosen via radio buttons.</para>

<figure id="export-page">
<title>Export Page</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_export_page.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>You can choose to export the topic map with or without the system
topics (those topics that make up the constraints or rules for using the
ontology). In general, other downstream applications such as browsers
will neither understand nor need the schema topics. The export is done
to a browser window and can be saved from there.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Saving a topic map</title>

<para>Any modifications made in an editing page will be sent to the
server immediately and written into the topic map. The application is
AJAX based, so modification are sent to the server as soon as they are
made. If an error occurs, the user may be redirected to a page showing
the errors instead of the intended destination.</para>

<para>The back button will work in the way it generally does on the
web, and will return to the previous page or to the previous state of
the current page. Note that previous page may be slightly out of date
if any changes were made to the topic since it was displayed the first
time.</para>

<important>
<para>Changes to your topic map are <emphasis>not</emphasis>
automatically persisted to disk on the server unless you are using
&ted; with the relational database backend of the Ontopia Knowledge
Suite. With the free version of &ted;, which operates in-memory, it is
necessary to press the <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button in order to
save the topic map to disk: pressing the
<guibutton>Confirm</guibutton> does <emphasis>not</emphasis> save to
disk; it merely submits the current page and updates the topic map
<emphasis>in memory</emphasis>.</para>
</important>
</section>
</section>

<section id="IE">
<title>Using Instance Editing Pages</title>

<para>The Instance Editing Pages are used to create instance topics
conforming to the ontology and constraints developed using the Type
Configuration Pages.</para>

<section id="inst-indexes">
<title>Topic Type Index Page</title>

<para>When you choose the <guilabel>Instances</guilabel> tab, you will
land at the instance index of all topic types. If your ontology includes
a type hierarchy, you will be able to show the complete tree by clicking
on <guilabel>Expand all nodes</guilabel>, with the result as shown in
<xref linkend="inst-topic-types-index"/>. Topic types that are allowed
to have instances are shown as links.</para>

<figure id="inst-topic-types-index">
<title>Topic Type Index Page</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_inst_topic_types_1.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>From this index, you can choose a topic type to see a list of
instance topics of that type (see <xref
linkend="inst-single-type-index"/>).</para>

<section id="inst-index">
<title>Instance Index Pages</title>

<figure id="inst-single-type-index">
<title>Instance Index Page</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_inst_topic_types_2.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>Choose an existing instance topic from the Instance Index, or
<guibutton>Create</guibutton> a new instance, to access the Instance
Editing Page.</para>
</section>

<section id="instance-page">
<title>Instance Editing Page</title>

<para>The Instance Editing Page is used to edit individual instance
topics, and is the most central page in &ted;, since most editing will
happen here. The contents on the page are entirely determined by the
ontology and schema for the topic type (see <xref
linkend="tt-config-page"/> for more on the Topic Type Configuration
Page). All the allowable fields for a topic type are available on the
Instance Editing Page, along with the allowable values for those
fields.</para>

<figure id="inst-topic">
<title>Instance Editing Page</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_inst_topic_types_3.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>When editing a topic there may be validation errors. These
usually occur when values are missing or when there are too many
values for a given field. The error messages shows up right above the
individual field. The topic map can be saved while there are
validation errors.</para>

<figure id="instance-field-validation-error">
<title>Field with validation error</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_required_edits.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>
</section>

<section>
<title>Changing a topic&#8217;s type</title>

<para>Frequently, it is easier to create a new instance from another
instance, rather than going back to the Instance Index Page. However
the next instance to be created might be of a different type than the
current one. In such cases, the instance author can use the
<guilabel>Change the topic type</guilabel> choice in the
Action Items Panel immediately upon accessing the new Instance Editing
Page, picking the new type from the drop-down box.</para>

<para>There are other times when changing the topic type will be useful.
For example, in an employee database, employees might be typed by their
status, such as probationary, tenured, retired, etc. As their status
changes, their topic type might change as well.</para>

<para>Changing a topic&#8217;s type can lead to a number of knock-on
effects that require action. For illustration purposes in <xref
linkend="change-type"/>, the <emphasis>Individual Artist</emphasis>
type topic <emphasis>Sir Paul McCartney</emphasis> has been changed to
an <emphasis>Album</emphasis> type topic. Now a new set of fields will
be displayed for the topic. Some of the fields are the same:
<emphasis>Name</emphasis>, <emphasis>Subject identifier</emphasis> and
<emphasis>Description</emphasis>, while <emphasis>Contains
track</emphasis> and <emphasis>Album created by</emphasis> replaces
<emphasis>Nickname</emphasis>, <emphasis>Is/was a Member of</emphasis>
and <emphasis>Created album</emphasis>. The user interface now
complains that information is missing in the <emphasis>Contains
track</emphasis>. Note that the information from the old fields are
still stored on the topic, but the fields are not presented in the
user interface. Changing the topic type back to <emphasis>Individual
artist</emphasis> will again show the original fields with the
original values.</para>

<figure id="change-type">
<title>Messages when changing a topic&#8217;s type</title>
<graphic fileref="images/doc_change_type.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>
</section>

<section id="topic-select-dialog">
<title>Assigning topics to associations</title>

<para>You can create new topics by clicking the &create; icon. If
there are multiple topic types that can participate in the
association, then you will be presented with a context menu, like the
one below, where you can select the topic type of the new
instance.</para>

<figure id="association-create-player-context-menu">
<title>Create player context menu</title>
<graphic fileref="images/association-create-player-context-menu.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>A new instance will then be created and associated to the
current topic. A popup window will then open and let you edit some
basic information about the new instance. Close the popup by clicking
the <guilabel>OK</guilabel> button or the <guilabel>X</guilabel> in
the top right corner.</para>

<figure id="association-create-player">
<title>Create player popup window</title>
<graphic fileref="images/association-create-player.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>
By default topics at the other end of associations are selected using
drop-down boxes, but this can be changed in the configuration of the
association type in the <guilabel>Interface control</guilabel>
field. The alternative for interface control are: <guilabel>Drop-down
list</guilabel>, <guilabel>Search dialog</guilabel>, <guilabel>Browse
dialog</guilabel>, and <guilabel>Auto-complete</guilabel>.</para>

<para>This is what the default drop-down list looks like. You may have
to press &add; before it shows up.</para>

<figure>
  <title>A drop-down list</title>
  <graphic fileref="images/drop-down-list.png"/>
</figure>

<para>The interface controls <guilabel>Search dialog</guilabel> and
<guilabel>Browse dialog</guilabel> use a popup dialog where the user
can either search for the topic to associate with, or browse for it.</para>

<para>If we change the example topic map so that to select an album
created by an artist you have to use the dialog, the instance editing
page from <xref linkend="inst-topic"/> would have a little search
button instead of the drop-down box.</para>

<figure>
  <title>The search button</title>
  <graphic fileref="images/search-button.png"/>
</figure>

<para> Pressing the &search; icon would open a new window as shown in
the figure below.
</para>

<figure>
  <title>The search dialog</title>
  <graphic fileref="images/search-dialog.png"/>
</figure>

<para>
Here you can do a search, and create associations to the topics you
find, or you can click "Browse" and see a list of the topics you could
create an association to. Below is shown the screen you get in this
case by clicking "Browse". This is also the dialog you would get if
the interface control had been <guilabel>Browse dialog</guilabel>.
</para>

<para>
Note that it's possible to control what shows on the browse screen by
configuring the topic type. It's possible to make the topics be shown
in a hierarchy, or to make it impossible to display the list of topics
(because the list is too big). See <xref
linkend="tt-config-standard-advanced"/> for more information.
</para>

<figure>
  <title>The browse dialog</title>
  <graphic fileref="images/browse-dialog.png"/>
</figure>

<para>
If the interface control is <guilabel>Auto-complete</guilabel> you
will get an input text field. You may have to press &add;
before the input field shows up. Below you can see an example of what
this interface control looks like. Once you start typing a list of
matching topics show up in a list below the input field. Note that the
auto-complete field runs a full-text query to retrieve the topics to
display in the list. (Note: the syntax of a full-text query currently
depends on the full-text engine used. This is likely to change in the
future.)
</para>

<figure>
  <title>The auto-complete input box</title>
  <graphic fileref="images/auto-complete.png"/>
</figure>
</section>


<section id="editing-occurrences">
<title>Editing name, occurrence, and identity fields</title>

<para>Names are always entered in a standard text input field.</para>

<important><para>The new field value is sent to the server as soon as
the field looses its focus, so make sure, that when you're done
editing, to click outside of the input box or press the Tab key to
move to another field. This rule applies to all text input boxes in
the application.</para></important>

<figure>
  <title>Name field</title>
  <graphic fileref="images/name-field.png"/>
</figure>

<para>As mentioned in <xref linkend="occur-config-standard"/>, an
occurrence field have a data type. The default is
<emphasis>String</emphasis>. Occurrences with the data types
<emphasis>String</emphasis> and <emphasis>Number</emphasis> are
displayed as a standard input text field. Here is an example:
</para>

<figure>
  <title>String and numeric occurrences</title>
  <graphic fileref="images/occurrence-datatype-default.png"/>
</figure>

<para>Identity fields and occurrences with the data type
<emphasis>URI</emphasis> are displayed as an input text field, but
with an &goto; icon next to it. Clicking the icon will open the URI in
the web browser.</para>

<figure>
  <title>URI occurrences (and identity fields)</title>
  <graphic fileref="images/occurrence-datatype-uri.png"/>
</figure>

<para>Occurrences with the data types <emphasis>Date</emphasis> and
<emphasis>Datetime</emphasis> are displayed as a standard input text
field, but with a date picker widget attached.</para>

<figure>
  <title>Date and datetime occurrences</title>
  <graphic fileref="images/occurrence-datatype-date.png"/>
</figure>

<para>HTML occurrences can be edited using an embedded HTML editor
(currently <ulink
url="http://tinymce.moxiecode.com/">TinyMCE</ulink>). This editor
provides rich formatting capabilities, but allows you to edit the
actual HTML document.</para>

<warning><para>Note that this component will not automatically save
your edits. Instead click the &save-icon; to have your changes saved
to the server.</para></warning>

<figure>
  <title>HTML occurrences</title>
  <graphic fileref="images/occurrence-datatype-html.png"/>
</figure>

<para>Image occurrence fields lets you upload images and display them
in the instance editor. Click the <guilabel>Choose...</guilabel>
button to get a file chooser widget that lets you select an image file
from the file system. Once the file has been selected, click the
<guilabel>Upload</guilabel> to uploaded the image and create an
occurrence for it.</para>

<figure>
  <title>Uploading an image</title>
  <graphic fileref="images/occurrence-datatype-image-upload.png"/>
</figure>

<para>Here is an example of what the user interface looks like after
an image has been uploaded:</para>

<figure>
  <title>Image occurrences</title>
  <graphic fileref="images/occurrence-datatype-image.png"/>
</figure>

</section>

</section>
</section>

<!--section>
<title>Plug-ins</title>

<para>Ontopoly is extensible and comes with a set of pre-configured
plug-ins. These are described in this section.</para>

<section>
<title>Automatic classification</title>

<para>This section describes the plug-in used for semi-automatic
classification of information resources against a topic map. The
plug-in requires some setup and configuration before use, which is
described. <xref linkend="sect-classify-use"/> describes how to use
the plug-in once configured.</para>

<note>
  <para>This feature is not included in the OKS Samplers, only in the
  commercial editions of the OKS. If you do not have an OKS license
  but would like to evaluate this feature, please contact
  <email>sales@ontopia.net</email>, and we can arrange an evaluation
  license for you.</para>
</note>

<section id="classify-config01">
<title>Setup</title>

<para>
For the plug-in to work the ontology must be annotated (see <xref
linkend="ontology-annotation"/>) in order for the plug-in to know
which topic types can be classified, and which association types are
used for classification. This is done by associating the topic type to
be classified with the association type used for classification. In
other words, if you have a topic type "Document" and an association
type "is about" you will make an association of type "classification
type for" between "is about" and "Document". This will tell the
plug-in that topics of type "Document" are to be classified, and that
the "is about" association type is used for this.
</para>

<para>
There are two steps to the setup of the plug-in:
</para>

<orderedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>Add the plug-in ontology to the topic map. (Described in
    this section.)</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Annotate the ontology as described above. (Described in
    <xref linkend="classify-config02"/>.)</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>The first step is to import the following LTM fragment into the
topic map. The fragment contains the declarations of the
classification ontology. Importing can easily be done through the
<emphasis>Add</emphasis> plug-in in the Omnigator. Note that this
plug-in is not enabled by default, so you need to activate the plug-in
in the Omnigator <emphasis>Plug-ins</emphasis> plug-in first. The
<emphasis>Plug-ins</emphasis> plug-in can be found on the topic map
page.</para>

<figure id="classify-setup01">
<title>Enabling the Add plug-in</title>
<graphic fileref="images/classify-setup01.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<literallayout><![CDATA[#PREFIX on @"http://psi.ontopia.net/ontology/"
#PREFIX xsd @"http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#"
#PREFIX cl @"http://psi.ontopia.net/classify/"

[cl:score-threshold : on:occurrence-type = "Classification score threshold"]
[cl:score-threshold-with-candidates : on:occurrence-type = "Classification score threshold (with candidate topics)"]
on:has-datatype(cl:score-threshold : on:field, xsd:decimal : on:datatype)
on:has-datatype(cl:score-threshold-with-candidates : on:field, xsd:decimal : on:datatype)

on:has-field(on:association-type : on:topic-type, cl:score-threshold : on:field)
on:has-field(on:association-type : on:topic-type, cl:score-threshold-with-candidates : on:field)

on:has-cardinality(cl:score-threshold : on:field, on:cardinality-0-1 : on:cardinality, on:association-type : on:topic-type)
on:has-cardinality(cl:score-threshold-with-candidates : on:field, on:cardinality-0-1 : on:cardinality, on:association-type : on:topic-type)

[cl:classification-type : on:association-type = "Classification type"
                         = "Classification type" / cl:classified-topic-type
                         = "Classification type for" / cl:classified-association-type]
  [cl:classified-association-type : on:role-type = "Classified association type"]
  [cl:classified-topic-type : on:role-type = "Classified topic type"]

on:has-role(cl:classification-type : on:association-type, cl:classified-association-type : on:role-type)
on:has-role(cl:classification-type : on:association-type, cl:classified-topic-type : on:role-type)
on:has-field(cl:classification-type : on:field, on:topic-type : on:topic-type, cl:classified-topic-type : on:role-type)
on:has-field(cl:classification-type : on:field, on:association-type : on:topic-type, cl:classified-association-type : on:role-type)
on:has-cardinality(cl:classification-type : on:field, on:cardinality-0-M : on:cardinality, on:topic-type : on:topic-type, cl:classified-topic-type : on:role-type)
on:has-cardinality(cl:classification-type : on:field, on:cardinality-0-M : on:cardinality, on:association-type : on:topic-type, cl:classified-association-type : on:role-type)
on:use-control(cl:classification-type : on:association-type, cl:classified-topic-type : on:role-type, on:drop-down-list : on:interface-control)
on:use-control(cl:classification-type : on:association-type, cl:classified-association-type : on:role-type, on:drop-down-list : on:interface-control)
]]></literallayout>

<para>Copy the above LTM fragment into the text box in the plug-in as
seen below and click the <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button. This
will import the LTM fragment into the current topic map. Make sure
that you save the topic map once you've done this to make sure that
the changes are made persistent. You only have to import this fragment
once per topic map.</para>

<figure id="classify-setup02">
<title>Importing the LTM fragment</title>
<graphic fileref="images/classify-setup02.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>The LTM fragment will add a new association type,
<emphasis>Classification type</emphasis>, and two new occurrence
types, <emphasis>Classification score threshold</emphasis> and
<emphasis>Classification score threshold (with candidate
topics)</emphasis> to the topic map. The new types should now be found
in Ontopoly.</para>
</section>

<section id="classify-config02">
<title>Configuration</title>

<para>Once the topic map has been prepared for classification, as
described in the previous section, the next step is to configure the
topic map. This means telling Ontopoly which association types can be
used to classify which topic types.</para>

<para>First we need to enable ontology annotation. This can be enabled
by clicking the <emphasis>Enable ontology annotation</emphasis> button
on the <emphasis>Description</emphasis> tab. After the button has been
clicked it should say <guibutton>Disable</guibutton>.</para>

<figure id="classify-setup03">
<title>Enabling ontology annotation</title>
<graphic fileref="images/classify-setup03.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>Then we can go to the <emphasis>Instances</emphasis> tab to
check that ontology annotation really has been enabled. On the
screenshot below you can see that it has indeed been enabled because
of the entries in italic font.</para>

<figure id="classify-setup04">
<title>Ontology annotation has been enabled </title>
<graphic fileref="images/classify-setup04.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>Now follow the link to <emphasis>Assocation
type</emphasis>. This brings us to the list of association types in
the topic map. Click the link to the association type you want to make
a classification type.</para>

<figure id="classify-setup05">
<title>Making 'requires task' and 'Goal' classifiable</title>
<graphic fileref="images/classify-setup05.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>On the screenshot you can see that we chose the
<emphasis>requires task</emphasis> association type. We can now make
this association a classification association type by selecting the
topic type that should be classifiable through this association
type. Select the topic type from the drop-download called
<emphasis>Classification type for:</emphasis>. In our example we
selected the <emphasis>Goal</emphasis> topic type. This should make
the classification plug-in show up on the instance editing page for
instances of that topic type.</para>

<para>Next we should specifiy the score thresholds for which the
association type should be defaulted. These thresholds are used by the
classification plug-in to automatically propose association types
given the score of keywords. The score threshold means that keywords
with a relevance score equal to or higher than the threshold will be
automatically selected, and the second threshold is used in cases
where a topic already exists in the topic map for the keyword.</para>

<figure id="classify-setup06">
<title>Instance with classification plug-in enabled</title>
<graphic fileref="images/classify-setup06.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>We can now verify that instances of the
<emphasis>Goal</emphasis> topic type are classifiable. It is in this
case because the <emphasis>Classify</emphasis> plug-in is
visible on the instance pages for topics of this type.</para>

<para>If you now go to the <emphasis>Classify</emphasis> plug-in
you'll get the document upload form. Upload a document and you'll be
presented with a classification proposal. You'll see that the
<emphasis>requires task</emphasis> association type has been proposed
for some of the keywords as they have a score above the
threshold.</para>

<para>This concludes the neccessary configuration. You may repeat the
configuration steps for all the association types and topic types that
you want to be classifiable. Make sure that you save your topic map
when you're done.</para>
</section>

<section id="sect-classify-use">
<title>Using the plug-in</title>

<para>The plug-in lets the user upload a document and have it
automatically classified against the topic map. The user is presented
with a proposal for what associations can be created between the
current topic and the concepts represented by keywords extracted from
the classified document.</para>

<para>The supported document formats are: HTML, XML, Acrobat PDF,
Microsoft Word, Microsoft PowerPoint and plain-text. If the document
format cannot be recognized the document will be loaded as
plain-text. If the result shows up as garbled characters, then the
document format was not properly recognized. If that happens try
changing the file name extension to help the format detector.</para>

<para>Two languages, English and Norwegian, are currently
supported. Documents in other languages may also be processed, but
results are likely to be poor. If you need support for another
language, please contact Ontopia.</para>

<figure id="classify-plugin01">
<title>Instance editing page with link to classification plug-in</title>
<graphic fileref="images/classify-plugin01.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>The plug-in is only visible on the instance editing page, see
<xref linkend="instance-page"/>, and only for instances of topic types
that have been registered as classifiable topic types. On the above
screenshot the topic type "paper" has been registered as such a
classifiable type and for that reason the "Upload and classify
document" menu item shows up in the menu on the right-hand
side.</para>

<figure id="classify-plugin02">
<title>Document upload form</title>
<graphic fileref="images/classify-plugin02.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>The user can select the "Classify" link and is then presented
with a page for uploading a document. Once the document file has been
chosen and the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button has been clicked the
document is classified and the user presented with the classification
result, such as the one seen below. (Note that it is possible to add
code to do the upload automatically. For more information on this,
please contact Ontopia.)</para>

<figure id="classify-plugin03">
<title>Classification page with keywords and proposed associations</title>
<graphic fileref="images/classify-plugin03.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>The classification result is a proposal for how the keywords in
the document can be associated with the current topic. The user is
presented with a ranked list of keywords that were found in the
document. Seven items are displayed for each keyword, each in its
separate column. Below we describe each column in sequence from left
to right.
</para>

<orderedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>The initial checkbox controls whether or not to make an
    association for the keyword on that row. If the checkbox is
    checked an association will be created; if not, nothing happens
    with that row.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>The drop-down list is used to select which type of
    association should connect the document topic with the keyword
    topic. The choices shown here are the classification association
    types for the document topic type. </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>The "Keyword" text field is used to set the name of new
    topics. Note that if a topic is selected in the drop-down box
    under the heading "Topic" this text box has no effect.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>The search button can be used to blacklist the current term,
    in case it is a term we never want to create a topic for. It can
    also be used to find an already existing topic to create an
    association to, in case the topic already exists, but was not
    found by the classifier.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>If the classifier has found an existing topic for the
    keyword, then this is shown in the "Topic" drop-down list. If no
    existing topic has been found, but you want to create one, you
    need to set the name correctly in the "Keyword" text field, and
    then select the correct topic type in this drop-down list.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>The count column shows the number of times the term occurred
    in the processed document. This has no particular significance,
    and is just shown for your information.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>The score is a value between 0 and 100% which indicates the
    estimate of the relative relevance of each keyword given by the
    classifier. A higher value means that the keyword is thought more
    relevant by the classifier.</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>To complete the classification and create the associations the
<guibutton>OK</guibutton> must be clicked. Only keywords with the
initial checkbox checked will be created. In the figure below can be
seen the result of having pressed <guibutton>OK</guibutton> in the
above example. Two new associations were added.</para>

<figure id="classify-plugin04">
<title>Result of having classified a document</title>
<graphic fileref="images/classify-plugin04.png" width="75%"/>
</figure>

<para>The classification can be cancelled by clicking the
<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button. This will bring the client back
to the instance editing page.  If the wrong document was selected it
is possible to correct this by clicking the "New document"
button.</para>

<para>The plug-in maintains a custom persistent list of black-listed
keywords. Such keywords will be filtered out automatically. It is
possible to add keywords to this list by selecting the keywords (using
the checkboxes on the left-hand side) and clicking the <guibutton>Add
to Blacklist</guibutton> button. Be careful not to add any preselected
keywords. The black-list is stored in a file called
<filename>.oks/classify/blacklist.<emphasis>&lt;topicmap-id&gt;</emphasis></filename>
in the user's home directory. Note that the user is the operating
system user that executes the application server. The file is a
plain-text file with each black-listed keyword on a separate line. It
can be edited in an editor. If the file has been modified it will be
reloaded when the next document is classified.</para>

</section>
</section>
</section-->

<section>
<title>Using Ontopoly with multiple users</title>

<para>Although &ted; ships in a single-user configuration, there is
support for multiple users under the hood. This support consists
of:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Support for storing the topic map in a relational database using
the RDBMS backend. This enables Ontopoly to scale to much larger topic
maps, avoids having to explicitly save the topic map, and ensures that
multiple users can work against the same topic map without causing data
to become corrupt. To make use of this support the OKS Enterprise
Edition is required.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Support for concurrent editing. This support is always enabled in
all Ontopoly versions, and ensures through locking that two different
users cannot edit the same topic at the same time.</para>
</listitem>

<!--listitem>
<para>Support for access control. The commercial editions of the OKS
ship with support for requiring username/password login, and also
support for assigning any combination of three different privileges to
users. It is possible to store the user data in a topic map and to
manage it with a web application included in the OKS; alternatively some
third-party authentication mechanism may be used. The use of a topic map
to store the users is described below.</para>
</listitem-->
</itemizedlist>

<!--section>
<title>Access control</title>

<para>To start using Ontopoly with user access control, the first
thing that needs to be done is to turn access control on. This is done
by changing the <symbol>access_control</symbol> parameter in
<filename>web.xml</filename> to the state shown below. This will
effectively cause Ontopoly to perform
<emphasis>authorization</emphasis> checks for the current user.</para>

<literallayout><![CDATA[  <context-param>
    <param-name>access_control</param-name>
    <param-value>true</param-value>
    <description>
      Tells Ontopoly whether or not to use access control.
    </description>
  </context-param>]]></literallayout>

<para>In addition, <emphasis>authentication</emphasis> needs to be
turned on so that the application server starts actually enabling the
authentication. How to do this is described in the document called
<citetitle>User Management in the OKS - Developer's
Guide</citetitle>. The JAAS login module will expose the names of
user-groups and privileges as J2EE roles so that they can be used by
Ontopoly to authorize the user.</para>

<para>Ontopoly supports the following privileges:</para>

<informaltable>
<tgroup cols="2">
<tbody>
<row>
  <entry>administrator</entry>
  <entry>Ontopoly administrator. This user has full rights to the entire application, including the admin pages.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>ontology-editor</entry>
  <entry>Ontopoly ontology editor. Users with this privilege has full rights to the Ontopoly ontology editor.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>ontology-reader</entry>
  <entry>Ontopoly ontology reader. Users with this privilege has read-only access rights to the Ontopoly ontology editor.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>instance-editor</entry>
  <entry>Ontopoly instance editor. Users with this privilege has full rights to the Ontopoly instance editor.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>instance-reader</entry>
  <entry>Ontopoly instance reader. Users with this privilege has read-only access rights to the Ontopoly instance editor.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>

<para>Ontopoly will check privileges and user-group membership through
the <symbol>HttpServletRequest.isUserInRole(String roleName)</symbol>
method by default. The JAAS module does this transparently from data
in stored in the configured topic map, but you are free to use any
other authentication modules/realms as long as you expose the above
privileges.</para> 
</section-->
</section>

<appendix id="appA">
<title>User interface conventions</title>
<para>This section describes general aspects of &ted;&#8217;s user
interface.</para>

<section>
<title>&ted; page layout</title>
<para>Most &ted; pages have a similar layout. The major sections are
identified in <xref linkend="genlayout"/> and described below.</para>

<figure id="genlayout">
<title>Page layout</title>
<graphic fileref="images/general_layout-annotated.png" width="100%"/>
</figure>

<section>
<title>Application navigation</title>

<para>In the upper right hand corner of all &ted; pages and on the
&ots; Home Page, there is an application navigation bar.</para>

<table>
<title>Application navigation bar</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="one" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="two" colwidth="3*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Item</entry>
<entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><guilabel>Home</guilabel></entry>
<entry>Returns you to the &ots; Home Page.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><guilabel>Manage</guilabel></entry>
<entry>Accesses the Omnigator Manage page.
<note>
<para>This item will eventually take the user to an common Manage Page,
that can be used for &ted; or Omnigator.</para>
</note></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><guilabel>Feedback</guilabel></entry>
<entry>As you use &ted;, we hope that you will use this feedback form to
send us comments as they occur to you. However, please do not use the
<guilabel>feedback</guilabel> mechanism to report bugs. &ots; provides a
direct link to Ontobugs.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><guilabel>Support</guilabel></entry>
<entry>If you need an answer to a question, please use this form or send
email to <email>support@ontopia.net</email>.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><guilabel>About</guilabel></entry>
<entry>Information about the version of &ted; currently in use.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>

<section>
<title>Tabbed navigation</title>
<para>Once inside a topic map, there are four major tabs.</para>

<table>
<title>Tabbed items</title>
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colnum="1" colname="one"
colwidth="1*"/><colspec colnum="2" colname="two" colwidth="3*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Item</entry>
<entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><guilabel>Description</guilabel></entry>
<entry>Page where descriptive information about the current topic map as
a whole can be captured, see <xref linkend="topic-map-config"/>.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><guilabel>Admin</guilabel></entry>
<entry>Use this page to export the topic map into a preferred
serialization syntax, see
<xref linkend="export"/>.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><guilabel>Ontology</guilabel></entry>
<entry>Set of pages for configuring the ontology, i.e., defining the
topic, occurrence, association, role, and name type topics. When in
Ontology area, a secondary set of buttons occur that provide discrete
access to the preferred page, e.g., topic type, association type, etc.,
see <xref linkend="OE"/>.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><guilabel>Instances</guilabel></entry>
<entry>Set of pages for creating and editing instances of topic types
defined in the Ontology, see <xref linkend="IE"/>.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>The items in the tabs are also repeated at the bottom of each page
upon which the tabs occur.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Editing box</title>

<para>There are three items in the Editing Box:</para>

<table>
<title>Editing box items</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="one" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="two" colwidth="3*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Item</entry>
<entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><guilabel>Open...</guilabel></entry>
<entry>Takes you back to the Topic Map Index Page. If you do not save
before you use this button, all edits since your previous save will
<emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> be written to disk.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><guilabel>Save</guilabel></entry>
<entry>Saves the current topic map to disk. <note><para>Only available
for in-memory topic maps.</para></note></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Search box and <guibutton>Find</guibutton> button</entry>
<entry>Use to find the uses of a term within the open topic map.
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>

<section>
<title>Topic title</title>

<para>The name of the current topic type or topic instance appears in
red.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Action items panel</title>

<para>The item choices available in grey boxes on the right hand side of
the screen are dependent on the type of page you are viewing. The
following table includes all possible items as a reference.</para>

<table>
<title>Action items</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="one" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="two" colwidth="3*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Item</entry>
<entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><command>Topic types</command></entry>
<entry>Shows the topic types of this topic. If there are multiple
types you can switch between them by clicking the link for each topic
type.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><command>Views</command></entry>
<entry>Shows the field views declared for fields assigned to this
topic type. If there are multiple views you can switch between them by
clicking the link for each view.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><command>View instances of this type</command></entry>
<entry>Moves you from a Type Configuration Page to an Instance Index
Page. Provides the index of instances of the current type.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><command>View instances of same type</command></entry>
<entry>Moves you from a Type Configuration Page to an Instance Index
Page. Provides the index of instances of the topic type of the current
type.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><command>Edit the type of this instance</command></entry>
<entry>Moves you from an Instance Editing Page to a Type Configuration
Page. Provides the Topic Type Configuration Page for the type of the
current instance.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para><command>New instance</command> field</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Available on the Topic, Association, Occurrence, Role,
and Name Type Pages. Supply a name to create a new one of the same type.
You will be taken to the appropriate Type Configuration Page, which will
have the <emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis> you fill in here.</para>
<para>Also available on Instance Editing Pages. You will be taken to a
new Instance Editing Page, which will have the <guilabel>Name</guilabel>
you fill in here.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><command>Create new [typing_topic] type</command></entry>
<entry>Lets you create a new topic of the same type as the current
topic, or a full copy of the current topic. Provides a blank Type
Configuration Page for the current kind of typing topic (i.e., topic,
occurrence, association, role, or name). Similar to the previous, but
is accessed from a Type Configuration Page.  No
<guilabel>Name</guilabel> is filled in if this is not a copy.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><command>Change the topic type</command> drop-down
list</entry>
<entry>Available from Instance Editing Pages, it provides an easy way to
change the type of the current topic. You will be notified of fields
used on the current topic that are not available when you change type,
so that you can make the necessary decisions and edits.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para><command>Delete this topic</command></para></entry>
<entry>Deletes the current topic.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para><command>Browse this topic in Omnigator</command></para>
</entry>
<entry>Opens a new browser window at the Topic Page for the current
topic in the Omnigator. As you make changes to the current topic, you
will be able to see the changes in the Omnigator window following a
browser refresh. If you move away from the topic in &ted;, the Omnigator
will remain on the original topic even after refreshing the
browser.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>
<para><command>View this topic in Vizigator</command></para>
</entry>
<entry>Opens a new browser window with the current topic as the focus
topic in Vizigator.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>

<section>
<title>Topic fields</title>
<para>The fields specific to the topic being edited are dynamic. How
to assign new field and how to unassign them are covered in detail in
sections <xref linkend="OE"/> and <xref linkend="IE"/>.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Ontology typing topics access</title>

<para>Not shown in <xref linkend="genlayout"/>, but available on all the
Type Index Pages is a secondary navigation bar to facilitate navigation
from one Type Index Page to another (see <xref linkend="ot1"/> for an
example).</para>

<table width="100%">
<title>Access to typing topics</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="one" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="two" colwidth="3*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Item</entry>
<entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><command>Topic Types</command></entry>
<entry>Access to the Topic Type Index.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><command>Occurrence Types</command></entry>
<entry>Access to the Occurrence Type Index</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><command>Association Types</command></entry>
<entry>Access to the Association Type Index</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><command> Role Types</command></entry>
<entry>Access to the Role Type Index</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><command>Name Types</command></entry>
<entry>Access to the Name Type Index</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Icons</title>

<para>The icons described in the table below occur throughout all &ted;
pages.</para>

<table>
<title>Icon conventions</title>
<tgroup cols="3"><colspec colnum="1" colname="one"
colwidth="1*"/><colspec colnum="2" colname="two" colwidth="2*"/><colspec
colnum="3" colname="three" colwidth="4*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Icon</entry>
<entry>Name</entry>
<entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>&expand;</entry>
<entry>Expand</entry>
<entry>The boxed plus sign expands the under the current topic.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>&collapse;</entry>
<entry>Collapse</entry>
<entry>The boxed minus sign collapses the hierarchy under the current
topic.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>&box;</entry>
<entry>Blank box</entry>
<entry>The empty box precedes a topic that does not have any children
in the hierarchy, and so, cannot be expanded or collapsed.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>&goto;</entry>
<entry>Goto</entry>
<entry>The right double arrow icon is always used to navigate to
another page. If the icon is located next to a text field that
contains a URI, the client browser will open the page pointed to by
the address. In the fields editor on the Topic Type Configuration Page
the icon is used to navigate to the topic type that declared the
field. This means that the field is an inherited field.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>&dnd;</entry>
<entry>Reorder</entry>
<entry>Used to change the order of fields in the Topic Type
Configuration Page, and to change the order of field values on the
instance editing page.</entry>
</row>
<!-- These are not icons and they are in any case self-explanatory -->
<!--
<row>
<entry><command>Expand all nodes</command></entry>
<entry>Expand All</entry>
<entry>Expands the entire supertype/subtype hierarchy under topic
types.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><command>Collapse all nodes</command></entry>
<entry>Collapse All</entry>
<entry>Collapses the entire supertype/subtype hierarchy under topic
types.</entry>
</row>
-->
<row>
<entry>&add-field;</entry>
<entry>Show input field</entry>
<entry>
<para>On an Instance Editing Page, the circled plus sign is used to
show a new input field so that one can add a new field value.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>&remove-field;</entry>
<entry>Hide input field</entry>
<entry>
<para>When used on the Instance Editing Page, the circled minus sign is
used to hide the input field.</para>

<para>When used on the Topic Type Configuration Page, it is used to
remove a value from an existing field or the use of the field
itself.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>&remove-value;</entry>
<entry>Remove value</entry>
<entry>
<para>When used on the Instance Editing Page, the small circled minus
sign is used to remove values from fields. In the fields editor on the
Topic Type Configuration Page the icon is used to unassign fields from
the topic type.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>&create;</entry>
<entry>Create</entry>
<entry>The circled asterisk is always used to create a new topic. Where
it occurs will control what type of topic is created at that point.
Where a choice of topic types is available, a pop-up menu will be
presented.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>&help;</entry>
<entry>Contextual help</entry>
<entry>The question mark in a green circle provides access to this User
Guide.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>

<section>
<title>Keyboard navigation</title>

<para>&ted; has no special support for keyboard navigation. In other
words, the keyboard navigation is as provided by your browser. This
means the following:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>
<formalpara>
<title>Opera</title>
<para>First tab key press puts the cursor into the first control on
the page. Following tab presses go to following controls, including
buttons.  Drop-down lists can be navigated with the arrow keys, and
pressing a letter will jump to the first item whose name begins with
that letter.</para>
</formalpara>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<formalpara>
<title>Firefox</title>
<para>As for Opera, except that links are included in the tab
cycle.</para>
</formalpara>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<formalpara>
<title>Internet Explorer</title>
<para>As for Firefox, except that URL bar is first in tab cycle.</para>
</formalpara>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</section>
</appendix>

<appendix id="appB">
<title>Scope of use</title>

<para>&ted; is designed for creating and editing topic maps conforming
to ISO/IEC 13250:2003.</para>

<para>The initial release of &ted; does not have support for all of the
features defined in the ISO standard. As more is known of user
requirements, some of these features may be added. We encourage users to
provide feedback using the
<guibutton>Feedback</guibutton> button available on all &ted; pages.
Unsupported features and usage constraints currently include:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<formalpara>
<title>Scope</title>
<para>Not supported.</para>
</formalpara>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<formalpara>
<title>Variant names</title>
<para>Not supported.</para>
</formalpara>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<formalpara>
<title>Reification</title>
<para>Not supported.</para>
</formalpara>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<formalpara>
<title>Merging</title>
<para>Not supported.</para>
</formalpara>
</listitem>

<!--listitem>
<formalpara>
<title>One and only one type for a topic</title>
<para>It is not possible to create topics that do not have a type.
Further, it is not possible to designate a topic as being of more than
one type.</para>
</formalpara>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<formalpara>
<title>Only one supertype for a topic type</title>
<para>It is not possible to give a topic type more than one supertype.</para>
</formalpara>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<formalpara>
<title>Item identifiers</title>
<para>Item identifiers (previously called source locators) cannot be
edited at all. These have no end-user significance, and so this feature
is unlikely to be added in the future.</para>
</formalpara>
</listitem-->
</itemizedlist>
</appendix>

<!--<appendix id="appC">
<title>License configurations</title>
<para>&ted; is licensed for use within other Ontopia products:
<itemizedlist>
<title>standalone version of &ted;</title>
<listitem>
<para>&ted; is part of the Omnigator free download and available for
use by a single user. There is no user management available in this
configuration</para>

</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist>
<title>toolkit version of &ted;</title>
<listitem>
<para>&ted; wil also become part of the Developer and Runtime
licenses. In a Developer license, &ted; may be used by a single user. More
significantly, &ted; can be built into a complete application that would be
available to mutliple users using a Runtime license of the OKS. Application
designers may also modify &ted;&#8217;s look-and-feel. User management is available
to grant or restrict access to the specific components, see
<xref linkend="components"/></para>

<para>In the Professional Edition, the edits to the topic map are
held in memory until the user presses the
<command>Save</command> button, when the topic map is written to
file storage.</para>

<para>In the Enterprise Edition, the edits are continually saved to
the user&#8217;s choice of RDBMS.</para>

</listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>

</appendix>-->

<appendix>
<title>About this document</title>

<para>This user guide provides a general theory of operation of &ted;.
It gives an introduction to its use and guidance on how to access the
various functions of the product, but is not meant to be an exhaustive
reference manual. Portions of this document serve as the target of links
from the contextual help within the product.</para>

<para>This document is focused on the use of &ted; and does not provide
training on the development of ontologies and topic maps in general. To
read more about those subjects, please see the
<ulink url="http://www.ontopia.net/">Ontopia Website</ulink>,
particularly the areas on <emphasis role="bold">topic
mapping</emphasis>.</para>

</appendix>
</article>
